<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The relation of a wonderfull voiage made by VVilliam Cornelison Schouten of Horne Shewing how south from the Straights of Magelan, in Terra Del-fuogo: he found and discouered a newe passage through the great South Sea, and that way sayled round about the world. Describing what islands, countries, people, and strange aduentures he found in his saide passage.</title>
            <title>Journal ofte beschryvinghe van de wonderlicke reyse. English</title>
            <author>Schouten, Willem Corneliszoon, d. 1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21828</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116796</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852012</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852012</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17309</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11585)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17309)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 937:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The relation of a wonderfull voiage made by VVilliam Cornelison Schouten of Horne Shewing how south from the Straights of Magelan, in Terra Del-fuogo: he found and discouered a newe passage through the great South Sea, and that way sayled round about the world. Describing what islands, countries, people, and strange aduentures he found in his saide passage.</title>
                  <title>Journal ofte beschryvinghe van de wonderlicke reyse. English</title>
                  <author>Schouten, Willem Corneliszoon, d. 1625.</author>
                  <author>Phillip, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36, 36-82, [1] p. : map (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by T[homas] D[awson] for Nathanaell Newbery, and are to be sold at the signe of the Starre, vnder S. Peters in Corne-hill, and in Pope-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Journal ofte beschryvinghe van de wonderlicke reyse.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: W.P., i.e. William Phillip.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A voyage about the vvorld by a new passage.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Voyages around the world --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oceania --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17309:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RELATION OF a Wonderfull Voiage made by <hi>WILLIAM CORNELISON SCHOVTEN</hi> of Horne.</p>
            <p>Shewing how South from the Straights of <hi>Magelan,</hi> in <hi>Terra Del-fuogo:</hi> he found and diſcouered a newe paſſage through the great South Sea, and that way ſayled round about the world.</p>
            <p>Deſcribing what <hi>Iſlands, Countries, People,</hi> and ſtrange Aduentures he found in his ſaide Paſſage.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>map showing new passage through the great South Sea south of the Straits of Magellan in Tierra del Fuego</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted by <hi>T.D.</hi> for NATHANAELL NEVVBERY, and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Starre, vnder <hi>S. Peters</hi> in Corne-hill, and in <hi>Pope-head Alley.</hi> 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17309:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17309:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL Sir <hi>THOMAS SMITH</hi> Knight, Gouernour of the <hi>Eaſt Indian Companie. &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Treatiſe of the Deſcription of a Voyage, made by <hi>VVilliam Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neliſon Schouten</hi> of <hi>Horne,</hi> by a newe vnexpected and neuer heretofore diſcouered Paſſage, by him found out in <hi>Terra del-Fuogo</hi> Southward, from the Straights of <hi>Magelan,</hi> into the great South ſea, and that way into the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> and ſo round about the World: comming to my hands I iudged no man more fitte (for the protection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) then your Worſhip, not onely becauſe of the great deſire you haue, and paines you dayly take to aduance ſuch trauels: but alſo in regard of your place of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the <hi>Eaſt Indian Company,</hi> whom this Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age ſpecially concerneth. If it pleaſe you to accept it, I ſhall thinke my paines well beſtow'd in the tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof out of the Dutch, wherein it was written: wiſhing it a meanes to further and aduance your trade in <hi>India:</hi> and to your Worſhip health in this worlde, and eternall felicitie in the world to come.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips to command, <hi>W. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:17309:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17309:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PRFEACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE generall <hi>States</hi> of the vnited <hi>Netherland Prouinces,</hi> hauing granted their Letters Pattens to the <hi>Eaſt India Company</hi> reſident in the ſayd <hi>Prouinces,</hi> to trafficke into the <hi>Indies,</hi> and none others but they onely, with a ſtricke prohibition vnto all other Marchants, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the ſayd Countries, not to ſayle or trafficke Eaſtward beyond the Cape <hi>de bona eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> nor through the Sraights of <hi>Magelan</hi> Weſtward, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into <hi>India,</hi> or any other vnknowne or not diſcouered coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. <hi>Iſaack le Maire</hi> a rich Marchant of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Egmont,</hi> hauing a great deſire to trafficke into ſtrange and farre Countries, and <hi>William Corneliſon Schouten</hi> of <hi>Horne,</hi> (a man well experienced in Seafaring, who before that time had ſayled thrice into moſt partes of the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> for Maiſter, Pilot, and Marchant) and yet verie deſirous to ſayle into and to diſcouer new and vnknowne Countries, oftentimes ſpeaking and conferring together, reaſoned among themſelues, whether they might not enter into the great South ſea, by an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, (then through the ſame wayes which in the <hi>Eaſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Companies</hi> Letters Pattents are formerly forbidden &amp; prohibited.) There to diſcouer great and rich Countries, where they might lade their ſhips with rich wares and marchandiſes,
<pb facs="tcp:17309:4"/>whereof the ſayd <hi>le Maire,</hi> affirmed he had ſome knowledge, and that if it did not fal out as they deſired, yet that they might paſſe through the afore ſaid great South ſeas, into the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> and there trafficke freely with great profite: vpon which conference at the laſt they agreed together, to make a diſcouery through the South vndiſcouered and vnknowne part of the World, South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from the Straights of <hi>Magelan,</hi> to ſeeke out a paſſage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſayd South Sea, which they thought very likely to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: for diuers circumſtances and reaſons to them knowne and by others at ſundry times found about the ſayd Straights of <hi>Magelan.</hi> And to that end agreed, betweene them to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe ſuch a Voiage, taking order that <hi>Iſaac le Maire</hi> ſhould prouide the one halfe of the money, and <hi>William Corneliſon Schouten</hi> the other halfe, to furniſh the ſaid Voiage, by the help and furtherance of their friendes, the care whereof, and to make prouiſion for the ſayd voyage being referred to <hi>William Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neliſon Schouten,</hi> who to effect the ſame, procured <hi>Peter Clementſon</hi> a Brewer, an ancient Burger Maiſter of <hi>Horne, Iohn Ianſon Molenwerf</hi> one of the Schepen, <hi>Iohn Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentſon Keis</hi> Senatour of the ſayd Towne, and <hi>Cornelius Segetſon</hi> a Marchant of <hi>Horne,</hi> to contribute in the ſame with them, and they together with the aforeſayd <hi>William Schouten, Iſaac le Maire</hi> and <hi>Iacob le Maire</hi> his Sonne, in ſhort time prepared ſo much money, as they thought conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and ſufficient for the ſayd voyage, not once making knowne to the owners of the ſhips, what their pretence was touching the ſayd voyage, but kept that ſecret to themſelues that diſburſed the money for the ſame.</p>
            <p>And to finiſh the ſayd voyage, the Marchants aforeſayd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and rigged a great and a ſmall ſhip of <hi>Horne,</hi> The great ſhip called the <hi>Vnitie,</hi> of <hi>360.</hi> tuns whereof <hi>William Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſon Schouten</hi> was Maiſter and cheife Pilot, and <hi>Iacob le
<pb facs="tcp:17309:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Maire</hi> Marchant and principall Factor, in it hauing <hi>65.</hi> men, and <hi>19.</hi> great peices, and <hi>12.</hi> ſlings, with muskets and other munition for warre proportionably, with a Pinnace to ſayle, an other to row, a boate, and a Scute, anekors, cabells, ropes, ſayles, and all other neceſſaries belonging thereunto. The leſſer ſhipp called the <hi>Horne,</hi> of <hi>110.</hi> tuns, whereof <hi>Iohn Corneliſon Schouten</hi> was Maiſter, and <hi>Aris Clawſon</hi> Marchant, in it <hi>22.</hi> men, <hi>8.</hi> great peices, <hi>4.</hi> ſlings, and other furniture as neede required, and was neceſſary for ſuch a voyage. And for that they would not make knowne to any man as I ſayd before whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they meant to goe, they hyred all their men, both common Saylers and Officers to ſayle vnto euery place whether the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and the Marchants would goe, which made the common ſaylers and people to ſpeake and geſſe of that voyage diuerſly, and at the laſt gaue them the name of the gold finders, but the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants named them the South Company. The ſhips being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, vpon the <hi>16</hi> of May <hi>1615.</hi> the men were muſtred by the Scout and Schepen of <hi>Horne,</hi> and the <hi>25.</hi> of the ſame moneth the <hi>Vnitie</hi> ſet ſayle, and arriued at the <hi>Teſſell</hi> vpon the <hi>27.</hi> The <hi>3.</hi> of Iune, the leſſer departed from <hi>Horne,</hi> and the next day came to the <hi>Teſſell:</hi> What further happened and fell out vnto them during the ſayd voyage, is in this Booke at large ſet downe, and declared from the reportes and writings of thoſe that ſaw and tryed the ſame, and which in the ſame voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age were the cheife and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall perſons.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17309:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17309:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE RELATION OF A Wonderfull Voiage made by <hi>VVILLIAM CORNELISON SCHOVTEN</hi> of Horne. Shewing how South from the Straights of <hi>Magelan,</hi> in <hi>Terra Delfuogo:</hi> he found and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered a newe paſſage through the great South Seaes, and that way ſayled round about the world. Deſcribing what <hi>Iſlands, Countries, People,</hi> and ſtrange Aduentures he found in his ſaide Voiage.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>PON the 14. of Iune 1615. wee ſayled out of the <hi>Teſſell,</hi> and the 16. of the ſame month, being in ſight of <hi>Dunkerke,</hi> paſt between <hi>Douer</hi> and <hi>Callis:</hi> the 17. anko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the Downs, <hi>William Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neliſon Shouten</hi> went on ſhoare at <hi>Douer</hi> to gette men to bring vs freſh water, and the ſame day ſet ſaile from thence, about euening by the Shingles meeting with a great fleete of Holland Ships laden with ſalt. The 21. and 22. hauing a great ſtorme wee put into the Iſle of of Wight, where our Maiſter would gladly haue hyred a carpenter but could not.</p>
            <p>The 25. we ſet ſayle from Wight, and vpon the 27. en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred at <hi>Plimmouth,</hi> where the Maiſter hyred a carpenter of <hi>Maydenblicke.</hi> The 28. we leaft <hi>Plimmouth</hi> and ſayled with
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17309:6"/>a north north eaſt wind and faire whether, and the 29. the Maiſter and Marc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt of the <hi>Horne</hi> came abord the <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> to agree together about order to be taken vpon the 4. of Iuly, for ſharing of our victuales, according to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and cuſtome vſed in ſhippes that ſayle long voiages, where they deliuer the ſaylers their meate and drinke by waight, and meaſure, to euery man alike and according to his qualitie.</p>
            <p>The 4. of Iuly, according to the aforeſaid reſolution, it was ordred that euery man ſhould haue a can of beere a day, 4. pound of bisket, and halfe a pound of butter (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſweete ſuet) a weeke, and fiue cheeſes for the whole voiage.</p>
            <p>The 8. being vnder 39. degrees and 25. minutes right againſt the Baſſels, our carpenters Mate dyed.</p>
            <p>The 9. and 10. with a north and north eaſt winde and a ſtife gale, the 11. we had a ſight of <hi>Porto Santo</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dera,</hi> and held our courſe eaſt.</p>
            <p>The 12. in the morning we ſaw the Saluages, which we leaft on backe-bord about 2. leagues from vs.</p>
            <p>The 13. in the morning wee ſaw the Ilands of <hi>Teneri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa,</hi> and great <hi>Canaena,</hi> and the ſame day about noone wee ſayld betweene them both with a ſtiffe north north eaſt wind, and a ſwift ſtreame.</p>
            <p>Betweene the 14. and the 15. with the ſame wind and ſtreame we paſſed <hi>Tropicus Cancri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 16. in the morning, with a Northeaſt wind, we found very hollow water, at which time the boate that was drawne at the Vnities ſtearne was full of water, and therewith the rope brake, and the boate ſunke and was loſt, which till that time we had drawne after the ſhip without any danger: about noone the ſame day we were
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17309:6"/>vnder 20. degrees and 30. minutes.</p>
            <p>The 17. and 18. with faire weathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and an indifferent wind north and northweſt, we ſailed weſt and by ſouth, and on the 19. in the morning were vnder 14. degrees and 45. minutes.</p>
            <p>The 20. on the morning we fell on the north ſide of Cape <hi>Verde,</hi> and had 8. fathome deepe when wee firſt ſaw the land, ſailing along by the coaſt, and at Sunne-ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Cape lay weſt and by ſouth from vs, ſo that with a north northeaſt wind we could not get beyond it, and were forced to ankor at 32. fathome deepe: that night it blew hard, with a great ſtorme of raine and thunder.</p>
            <p>The 21. in the morning the wind ſouth ſoutheaſt, and after Sun-riſing variable, we ſet ſaile with our courſe to to Seaward, firſt weſt and by north, then northweſt, and that whole day ſailed not aboue 6. leagues.</p>
            <p>The 22. we lay driuing all day long with a calme, and no ſailes vp: then Cape <hi>Verde</hi> lay eaſt from vs: about euening we ſaw a ſhip ſouthward, that held her courſe northweſt.</p>
            <p>The 23. in the morning hauing a South wind, wee could not reach aboue the Cape, but were forced to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kor, by reaſon of the ſtreame, about noone wee ſet ſaile, with a weſt wind, and got beyond the Cape, and that euening ankored within the ſecond Iſland, in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary roade, at 10. fathome deepe.</p>
            <p>The 24. it rained ſore, and we made ready to fetch freſh water from the land.</p>
            <p>The 25. the Alkaire, or gouernour came aboord our ſhip, with whome wee agreed for eight ſtates of Iron; that wee ſhould peaceably fetch freſh water from the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17309:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhore.</p>
            <p>The 26. it rained, and the weather very darke: the ſame day we ſaw a ſhip that ſailed towards vs, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kored two leagues from vs, vnder the land being a ſhip of <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> that came thither to trafficke along the coaſt.</p>
            <p>The 28. and 29. we fetcht water, meane time the <hi>Horne</hi> hoyſed ſaile, and went to the place where the ſhip of <hi>Rotterdam</hi> lay, in a Bay called <hi>Refreſco,</hi> to ſee if wee could there find any Limonds, but came againe in the euening, and could get none.</p>
            <p>The 31. there came a <hi>French</hi> ſhip and anchored by vs. The ſame day we had ſtayed a <hi>Negroes</hi> ſhip, who at night ſhewed vs a fit place to fiſh in, and our men carrying their nets on the firme land, tooke as many fiſhes of diuers ſorts, as both our ſhips could eate in two dayes.</p>
            <p>The firſt of Auguſt in the morning we ſet ſaile from Cape <hi>Verde,</hi> with the <hi>Rotterdamer,</hi> who at noone time left vs and ſet his courſe for the <hi>Salt Iſlands:</hi> all that time we had faire weather, and a fine gale of wind out of the north, our courſe ſouthweſt.</p>
            <p>The 2. we had faire weather, with a fine gale of wind, at which time we klled a little calfe, and a goate that we gotte at Cape <hi>Verde,</hi> which ſerued all our men in both ſhips, for a whole dayes meate.</p>
            <p>The 3. we had but ſmall wind, and that night faire weather, but when day appeared, it was thicke and clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, with thunder, raine, and lightning.</p>
            <p>The 4. about noone, we were vnder 12. degrees and 12. minutes, with very faire weather and a good ſwift gale, as alſo the 5. day.</p>
            <p>The 7.8. and 9. it rained faſt, but yet with an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17309:7"/>gale.</p>
            <p>The 10. it rained, with a ſmall wind that night we ſaw a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Barke vnder ſaile.</p>
            <p>The 15. we had a reaſonable freſh winde, and good weather, and made indifferent good way: then we ſaw great ſtore of birds called <hi>Rabos forcados,</hi> and tooke a <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rado.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 16. about noone we were vnder 7. degrees and 40. minutes, with faire weather and a good winde, as afore.</p>
            <p>The 17. at noone we were vnder 7. degrees 12. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, with faire weather, and an indifferent coole gale ſouthweſt: that day we tooke many <hi>Bouetes</hi> and <hi>Corret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 18. and 19. we lay by the wind, reſoluing to hold our courſe for <hi>Sierra Liona,</hi> there to refreſh our ſelues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many of our men had a great ſcouring, all that day we had a ſtiffe contrary wind, and were forced to lie by the weather, it being then too late to go ſpeeedily vnder the Line: and at the Cape we got but little refreſhing, at that time about noone we were vnder 7. degrees and 55. minutes.</p>
            <p>The 20. in the morning we were vnder 7. degrees 45. minutes, with faire weather, and a good gale of winde out of the South, wee helde our courſe Eaſt, and Eaſt and by North; at which time we ſaw great ſtore of land fowles, and change of water: about euening we caſt out the lead, and found 30. fathome ſandie ground, and had land almoſt 40. leagues nearer then we geſſed it to be, the ſame night we anchored at 16. fathome, and were vpon the weſt end of the <hi>Baixos,</hi> or ſhallows of <hi>S. Anna</hi> Iſland.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:17309:8"/>
            <p>The 21. in the morning, by Sunne riſing we ſet ſaile, and ſaw the high land of <hi>Sierra Liona,</hi> about 6. Leagues from vs Northeaſt and by North: wee likewiſe ſaw the Iſlands of <hi>Mabrabomba,</hi> which lie on the ſouth point or corner of the high land of <hi>Sierra Liona,</hi> north from the <hi>Baixos,</hi> or ſhallows of <hi>S. Annas</hi> Iſland. <hi>Sierra Liona</hi> is a very high land, there is no land ſo high as it betweene Capo <hi>Verde,</hi> and the coaſt of <hi>Guinea,</hi> whereby the poynt is moſt eaſie to bee knowne: that day wee laboured as we could to get to land, for the moſt part hauing ſtormie weather, running to the point, and ouer the <hi>Baixos,</hi> or ſhallows of <hi>S. Anna,</hi> at 10.9.8.7. and 5. fathome water, and as wee ſayled northward, the water waxed deeper, but eaſtward ſhallower, ſo that about euening we ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a high water, at foure fathome and a halfe ſoft ground, and in the night time we had but three fathome and a halfe, but it was fine cleare weather.</p>
            <p>The 22. in the morning at Sunriſing, <hi>William Schouten</hi> went aboord the <hi>Horne,</hi> and ſayled in it before vs, the great ſhip following, holding our courſe north northeaſt with a northweſt winde, and an ebbe vnder the bough, and ſo got off from the <hi>Baixos,</hi> to 18. fathome water, and from thence to the Iſlands of <hi>Mabrabomba,</hi> which are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry high, and lie all three on a row, ſouthweſt and north<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt, halfe a league from <hi>Sierra Liona</hi> to ſeaward, there we had ſhallow water at fiue and foure fathome, ſoft muddy ground, we anchored about a league from the land, and going on ſhore found no man dwelling therin, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the foote-ſteps of many great beaſtes, but all the land lay waſt like a wildernes, with low marſhes or bogs, and high hils.</p>
            <p>The 23. in the morning, <hi>Iacob le Maire</hi> went aboord
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17309:8"/>the <hi>Horne,</hi> and from it with both the boates on ſhore, where hee found a Riuer, at the mouth thereof hauing many cliffes, ſands, &amp; rockes, whereby no ſhip could goe into it, but within it was very deepe, and broad enough for ſhips to turne and wind, there they could perceiue no people to dwell, but ſaw three wilde Oxen, and a great many Monkeis, and ſome birds that barked like dogs. They rowed at leaſt 3. leagues vp into it with the floud and there found a wilde <hi>Palme</hi> tree, but in the euening came aboord againe, and heard of no people, neither found any fruit that might ſerue their turne to eate.</p>
            <p>The 24. both our Scouts went on ſhore againe to ſeeke for men or ſome refreſhing, each of them in a ſeuerall Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, at leaſt 5. leagues into it: <hi>Aris Clawſon</hi> the Marchant of the <hi>Horne,</hi> with one of the Aſſiſtants into the one, and <hi>Claus, Iohnſon, Ban,</hi> with our maſters mate in the other, and the 25. in the morning came on boord againe: The Marchant of the <hi>Horne</hi> had beene in a ſalt riuer, and brought with him 5. or 6. wilde <hi>Palmites, Claus, Iohnſon;</hi> and <hi>Ban,</hi> had beene in a freſh riuer, and there found a place wherein there grew 8. or 9. Limond trees, which they ſhooke, and got about 750. Limonds, moſt ripe, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to drie. There alſo they ſaw great ſtore of Tortoyſes, and ſome Crocodiles, but no people. We determined to trie if wee could get into the freſh Riuer with both our ſhippes, therein to make prouiſion of freſh water and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, and to that end ſet ſayle, but found the water ſo ſhallow, that we were forced to anchor at 6. fathome. The <hi>Horne</hi> anchored before the Riuer, on the lower land, but there found ſhallow water, by meanes of the point of the <hi>Baixos,</hi> or ſhallows of <hi>S. Anna</hi> Iſland. <hi>Iacob le Maire</hi> and <hi>Aris Clawſon,</hi> the marchants of the <hi>Horne</hi> and <hi>Vnitie,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17309:9"/>went with the boate vp into the riuer.</p>
            <p>The 26. we had a ſtiffe gale of winde South ſouthweſt, ſo that wee could not ſaile, yet the <hi>Horne</hi> beate on the ſouth point of the bay, which is about fiue leagues broad from the north to the ſouth ſide.</p>
            <p>The 27. in the morning we hoyſt anchor to ſayle to the <hi>Horne,</hi> and about noone time the <hi>Horne</hi> boate came with <hi>Iacob le Maire</hi> on boord againe, bringing with him about 1400. Limonds which they had found in diuers places here and there in the riuer. In the euening we got to the <hi>Horne,</hi> and there anchored at three fathome and a halfe, ſoft ground.</p>
            <p>The 28. our maſter went vp the riuer, before the which we lay with both the boates, and about euening came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and found no good land to goe vpon, nor any ſignes of men, but onely a Bull with a Calfe, all the ground being marſhie and full of trees that ſtood in the ſalt water.</p>
            <p>The 29. perceiuing that we were not in the riuer of <hi>Sierra Liona,</hi> we determined early in the morning to ſet ſayle, and to goe northward of the high land, and about noone wee got aboue the Iſlands of <hi>Mabrabonda,</hi> weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, along towards the north part of the high land, till we had 12. and 15. fathome water, and in the euening got about the point, where we anchored at 15. fathome deepe.</p>
            <p>The 30. in the morning, we hoyſed anchor, and draue with the ſtreame, and a ſouth wind before the village, in the right roade of <hi>Sierra Liona,</hi> where wee anchored at 8. fathome, ſandy ground, about a musket ſhot from the land, there we ſaw 8. or 9, houſes couered with ſtraw.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Moores</hi> called vnto vs in their Language, to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17309:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>fetch them aboord our ſhippe, and becauſe they had no Canoes we ſent our boate on land, which preſently came backe againe with 5. <hi>Moores</hi> in it, whereof one was their Interpreter: but before they came, they deſired that we would leaue ſome of our men, to ſtay with them as pledges, for that not long before there had beene a <hi>French</hi> ſhip there, which had taken and carryed away 2. of their <hi>Moores. Aris Clawſon</hi> the marchant that went a ſhore with the boate, ſtaied there with them, and haue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing certaine beades, he there bartered them for 700. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, moſt ripe, and two bunches of Banauas almoſt ripe alſo. The Interpreter ſpake all kind of Languages, one with an other. In the meane time, our men hauing faire weather, laded freſh water, which is there eaſie to be had, by reaſon it falles downe out of the hill into the roade, ſo that we held the barrels vnder the ſhore, or fall of the water, and filling them put them ſtraight into the Scute, the water was very good.</p>
            <p>The 31. when we had fild our veſſels full of water, and that morning <hi>Iacob le Maire, Aris Clawſon, Claus Iohnſon, Ban,</hi> and all the aſſiſtants went on land, and bartered for about 25000. Limonds, for a few beades, and ſome ſlight <hi>Norremburgh</hi> kniues, wee might haue had 100000. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds there at the leaſt, if we would, for there they grew by whole woods full: the ſame night we bartered with the <hi>Negroes</hi> for a ſhole of Fiſh.</p>
            <p>The firſt of September we hoyſed anchor, and draue before the ſtreame, and that euening anchored at the mouth of the Sea, before a ſmall Riuer.</p>
            <p>The 2. we ſet the <hi>Horne</hi> vpon the Strand to make her cleane, hauing a god place to doe it, for there the water falles 7. foote vp and downe, in the euening our men
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17309:10"/>came on boord againe, and brought a little beaſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med an Antelop, which they found in a wood, in a net or ſnare ſet there by the <hi>Negroes,</hi> and ſome Limonds, and after that the boate went out to fiſh, and got a greate number, and ſome Palmitas, which they had not cut downe in the wood.</p>
            <p>The 3. in the afternoone, the <hi>Horne</hi> being made cleane vvas lancht into the water againe, and our maſter went out to fiſh, in the euening bringing a great ſhole of fiſh with him, in faſhion like to a ſhoemakers cutting knife, and euery man 150 Limonds for his part.</p>
            <p>The 4. early in the morning, we hoyſed anchor, and ſet ſayle out of <hi>Sierra Liona,</hi> with an indifferent winde, but in the euening hauing contrary winde, anchored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine at 14. fadom, good anchor ground.</p>
            <p>The 5. In the firſt quarter, we hoyſt anchor againe, and ſayled with a calme, but in the third quarter ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe, at 14. fadome, ſandie ground.</p>
            <p>The 6. In the firſt quarter, we ſet ſayle againe, but the winde contrary, were forced to anchor at 12. fadome, ſandy ground, there we could ſtill ſee the land of <hi>Sierra Liona,</hi> in that place there went a ſtrong ſtreame.</p>
            <p>The 9. Wee ſet ſayle, but the wind contrary, vve an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chored in the euening, at 32. fadom ſandy ground.</p>
            <p>The 10. in the firſt quarter, hauing a ſouthweſt wind, we ſet ſayle, but the weather being calme, we let anchor fall, with our ſayles ſtill vp, and not long after, the wind beginning to riſe we hoyſt anchor, but in the third quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in a calme, anchored againe, at 29, fathom: the laſt quarter the wind beginning to blow, we ſet ſayle, but doe what we might we could not goe forward.</p>
            <p>The 11. we ſet ſayle, but anchored againe in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17309:10"/>quarter, by reaſon of the calme, there the ſtreame went northward. Not long after we hoyſed ſayle againe, with ſome ſmall wind, but it calmd againe, and the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waxed very thicke.</p>
            <p>The 12. Wee were vnder 9 degrees and 20. minutes, at euening we anchored at 17. fathom.</p>
            <p>The 15. We ſet ſayle with a weſt northweſt wind, all that quarter it rained, In the meane time, the <hi>Horne,</hi> in a thicke miſt ſayled out of our ſight, and we ſhot two pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, an houre betweene each ſhot, to call her, and about 10. of the clocke ſhee came againe.</p>
            <p>The 16. and 17. the vvind was variable, we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chored at 15. fathome, with rainie weather, yet the vvind blevv hard.</p>
            <p>The 18. about noone vve ſet ſayle, the <hi>Horne</hi> loſt an Anchor and Cable in the vvinding, the vvind blevv hard, and the vvater vvent ſomevvhat hollovv.</p>
            <p>The 19. Hauing contrary vvinde, and vve being very weary, by reaſon the vveather vvas rainy and ſtormie, vvee determined to goe backe againe to <hi>Sierra Liona,</hi> to refreſh our ſelues, and take in freſh vvater, but after noone hauing a good northvveſt vvind, vve changed our courſe ſouthvvard againe, and vvent forvvard.</p>
            <p>The 20. vvith a good vvinde vve ſayled ſouthvvard, and vvere vnder 8. degrees 30. minutes.</p>
            <p>The 21. and all that month out, vve had varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vvindes, vvith calmes, and euery day great ſtore of raine, and vpon the 30. day vve vvere vnder 5. degrees</p>
            <p>In the beginning of October, vve had variable vvindes, and ſome calmes, vvith great ſtore of raine, night and day.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:17309:11"/>
            <p>The 5. vve vvere vnder 4 degrees 27. minutes, the ſame day about noone there vvas ſuch a noiſe in the bough of our ſhippe, that the Maiſter beeing behinde in the Gallerie, thought that one of the men had fallen out of the fore ſhip, or from the boeſprit into the ſea, but as hee looked out ouer the ſide of the ſhip, he ſavv the Sea all red as if great ſtore of bloud had bin povvred into it, vvhereat he vvondred, knovving not vvhat it ment, but afterward he found, that a great fiſh or a ſea monſter hauing a horne had there vvith ſtricken againſt the ſhip, vvith moſt great ſtrength, for vvhen vve vvere in <hi>Porto Deſire,</hi> vvhere vvee ſet the ſhip on the ſtrand to make it cleane, about 7 foote vnder vvater before in the ſhip, vve found a horne ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſhip, much like for thickneſſe faſhion to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Elephants tooth, not hollow but full, very ſtrong hard bone, vvith had entered into three planckes of the ſhip, that is 2 thicke planckes of greene and one of Oken wood, and ſo into a rib, vvhere it turned vpvvard, to our great good fortune, for if it had entered betvveene the ribes into the ſhip, it vvould happely haue made a greater hole, and haue brought both ſhip and men in danger to be loſt, it ſtucke at leaſt halfe a foote deepe into the ſhip, and about halfe a foot vvithout, vvhere vvith great force it vvas broken of, by reaſon vvhere of the great monſter bled ſo much.</p>
            <p>The 6.7.8. variable windes and ſome raine, the 10. we tooke great ſtore of fiſh, and were vnder three degrees 30. minites, with South and variable windes for certaine dayes.</p>
            <p>The 15 we were vnder 2. degrees 35. minutes that day we tooke 40. Bouets.</p>
            <p>The 16. we were vnder one degree 45. minutes, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17309:11"/>day wee tooke great ſtore of fiſh, and ſaw many whales.</p>
            <p>The 19. and 20. about noone we paſt the equinoctiall line, and had a ſouth eaſt and a ſouth ſoutheaſt winde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the 24. and then an eaſt ſouth eaſt winde and held our courſe ſouth. The water being ſo hollow, that our blind ſaile was ſtricken in peeces with the ſea, that day at noone we were vnder 3. degrees 43. minutes ſouthward of the line.</p>
            <p>The 25. the winde continuing, we held on the ſame courſe, vntill that time we had ſailed, and no man in our ſhip, (vnleſſe it were the maſter, <hi>William Corneliſon Schou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> and <hi>Iacob le Maire</hi> our Marchant) knew whether wee ſhould go, and then they told vs what voyage they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which was, to ſeeke by an other way then the ſtraights of <hi>Magelan,</hi> to enter into the ſouth ſea, there to diſcouer new countries in the South parts, where they thought to finde great riches, and that if it fell not as they deſired and pretended, then that they would ſaile along through the great ſouth Sea, ſouthward to the eaſt <hi>Indies.</hi> This being knowne, our men were very glad and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, hoping euery man for his part, to benefit by that vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, to their aduancement.</p>
            <p>The 26. we were vnder 6 degrees, 25. minutes with faire weather and a good gale, and all the reſt of that moneth for the moſt part ſayling ſouthward, with an eaſt, and a northeaſt winde, we were vnder 10 degrees and 30. minutes.</p>
            <p>The firſt, of Nouember wee paſt the ſunne, whereby at noone time, it was North from vs.</p>
            <p>The third we were vnder 19 degrees 20 minutes, then we ſaw ſome blacke birds and two or three foules called ſea mewes, and after noone, we had a ſight of <hi>Martin vads
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17309:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ilands</hi> called <hi>Aſcenſion,</hi> which lay ſoutheaſt and by eaſt from vs, vnder 20 degrees, there we found our compaſſe to varrie Northeaſtward 12 degrees, The wind being North northeaſt, as the day before, and held our courſe South, That day our men had double allowance of wine, becauſe we had paſt the dangerous ſands called <hi>Abrothos.</hi> The day enſewing to the 10. wee held our courſe for the moſt part, ſouth and Southweſt and were vnder 25 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 33. minutes.</p>
            <p>The 11, we found our compaſſe to varie 17, degrees northeaſtward, and with a ſouth wind, held our courſe Weſt and weſt and by ſouth.</p>
            <p>The 12 with a ſoutheaſt, and by eaſt, and an eaſt winde we ſayled ſouth ſouthweſt and ſouthweſt, and were vnder 26 degrees 45 minutes.</p>
            <p>The 13, 14, and 15, wee ſailed ſouth, and ſouthweſt, with an eaſt winde.</p>
            <p>The 16, 17, and 18, the winde ſouth, we held for the moſt part weſt ſouth weſt, and were vnder 34, degrees 15. minutes, and ſaw much <hi>Walſchot</hi> driue.</p>
            <p>The 19. with a north and northeaſt wind, wee ſayled ſouth ſouth weſt, and perceiued that the ſtreame draue vs much to the ſouth.</p>
            <p>The 20. we were vnder 36. degrees 57. minutes there wee ſaw many Quallen driue, and a great number of ſea lice, which are a kind of lice for greatneſſe like to ſmall flies.</p>
            <p>The 21. we were vnder 38 degrees 25. minutes, and had alteration of water, there wee caſt out our leade but found no ground, the compaſſe then varied 17, degrees northeaſtward, that morning wee ſaw the new Moone being 21. howers old.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17309:12"/>
            <p>The 22 it was ordered by our maſter and his counſell, that one man ſhould haue a cup of ſacke euery day, and a meaſure of oyle weekely, our french wine and butter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all ſpent.</p>
            <p>The 23. we ſaw many Whales, and white water, and were vnder 40 degrees 56. minutes.</p>
            <p>The 24. we ſaw many more great fiſhes, and much Odenkwos driue, the water very hollow out of the weſt and ſaw many birds.</p>
            <p>The 30. we had white water, as if we had bin hard by the land, and were vnder 46. degrees 15. minutes, and ſaw many birds.</p>
            <p>The 2. of December being vnder 47. degrees 45. minutes we ſaw much <hi>Steencroſſe</hi> driue.</p>
            <p>The 4. we ſtill ſaw <hi>Steencroſſe</hi> white water, and many birds and were vnder 47 degrees 25 minutes, and 16. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees northeaſtward variation of the compaſſe, then wee caſt out our lead and found 75 fathom ſandy ground.</p>
            <p>The 5. wee caſt out our lead and had 65. fathom, ſavv many birds and <hi>Steencroſſe</hi> then we were vnder 46, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 25 minutes, and had 54. fathom, that night wee ſaw many Whales.</p>
            <p>The 6. in the morning vve had 46 fathom vvater and vvith a northvveſt vvinde ſayled vveſt ſouthvveſt, and at noone vvere vnder 40 degrees 37 minutes and had 42 fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vvater, about 4 in the after noone vvee ſavv land not very high, but vvhite and ſome vvhat flat, vvee fell (according to our deſire) on the north ſide of <hi>Porto Deſire</hi> and at night anchored at 10 fathom deepe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a league and a halfe from the ſhoare vvith an ebbe that ran Southvvard, as ſtrongly as the ſea runs betvveene <hi>Fluſhing</hi> heads.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:17309:13"/>
            <p>The 7. in the morning vve hoyſed anchor, and ſailed South, vntill noone, then vve vvere before the hauen of <hi>Porto Deſire,</hi> lying vnder 47. degrees 40, minutes, and made towards the entrie thereof, where we had very high water, ſo that the cliffes (wherof <hi>Oliuer van Noort</hi> writeth, vvhich ſayling into that hauen muſt be left northvvard from vs,) were cleane vnder water, but on the ſouth point there lay certaine cliffes open, which we tooke to be thoſe, and therefore went ſouthward on, but ſayled ſouthward of the right chanell into a crooked bay, and there at high water anchored at foure fathom and a halfe, and when the water was low, wee had but 14. footwater, whereby the <hi>Vnitie</hi> lay with her ſtearne faſt on ground, it being ful of cliffes, the wind was weſt from the land, &amp; ſmooth wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to our great fortune, for if wee had had an eaſt vvinde, vvith any gale, for certaine, vve had loſt our ſhip: vpon the cliffes vve found many eggs, and tooke great muſtles and other fiſh, and among the reſt ſmelts of 16 inches long, and for that cauſe vve called that place the <hi>Smelt bay,</hi> our Shallop vvent to the <hi>Pinguijns Iland,</hi> lying eaſt ſoutheaſt tvvo leagues from <hi>Porto Deſire,</hi> and came aboord againe late in the euening, bringing 2 ſea Lyons, and 150 <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guijns,</hi> vvhich vve eate the next day.</p>
            <p>The 8 in the morning, vvith the land vvind vve ſayled out of the <hi>Smelt bay,</hi> and anchored right before the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of <hi>Porto Deſire,</hi> and ſent our Shalop out to ſound the depth of the channell, and found 12 and 13 fathom, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering in after noone vvith a high vvater and a northeaſt wind wee ſet ſaile, the <hi>Horne</hi> firſt, and ſo entred into the hauen. When wee had ſayled about a league and a halfe into the riuer the winde turned, and we anchored at 20 fathom: there the ground vvas ſlippery ſtones, for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17309:13"/>about halfe an houre after, the winde blowing hard north weſt, both our ſhips lying with 2. anchors a peece out: preſently draue vpon the South ſhoare, for there 25: anchors could not haue holden them, ſo that wee verily thought both our ſhips would there be caſt away. The great ſhip ſat with herſide vpon the cliffes, and ſhoke with the falling water, ſome what lower, and ſtill kept ſtanch, but the <hi>Horne</hi> fell vpon the cliffes, ſo that the water went cleane from it, whereby at low water a man might haue gone drie foote vnder the keele, right againſt the maine maſt, the keele was aboue a fathom out of the water, feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be hould, but as the winde blew hard northweſt, it kept it from falling ouer, which appeared to be ſo, for that when the winde ceaſed, it fell from the land againſt the winde vpon the ſide, at leaſt three foote lower then the keele, whereat we were all abaſht, thinking wee had ſurely loſt her, but when the floud came with ſtill weather it roſe vp againe, whereat we all reioyced. In the morning with calme weather we wound of from the wall, and the ſame night the <hi>Horne</hi> came to vs.</p>
            <p>The 9. in the morning, we ſet ſayle againe, and went further into the riuer, and came to the <hi>Kings Iſland</hi> ſo called by <hi>Oliuer Van Noort,</hi> the <hi>Horne</hi> went behinde it, and there anchored, but we could not get in with the <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> becauſe the winde was contrarie, our men went on ſhore into the <hi>Iſland,</hi> which was almoſt couered ouerwith eggs, for a man ſtanding ſtill on his feete; with his hands might reach to 54. neaſts, each hauing 3 or 4 eggs a peece much like (but ſome what greater) then <hi>Sea-Mues</hi> eggs, the birdes were blackiſh <hi>Sea-mewes</hi> wee carried thouſands of them on board and eate them.</p>
            <p>The 10. our boate vvent on the north ſide of the riuer,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17309:14"/>to ſeeke for freſh vvater, but found none, for digging holes of 14. foote deepe, they found brackiſh vvater, both on the high hilles and in the valleys, and returning on boord againe, brought great ſtore of birds and egs vvith them.</p>
            <p>The 11. the boate vvent lovver into the Riuer on the ſouth ſide, to ſeeke for men and vvater, and found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but brackiſh vvater, there they ſavv ſome Eſtriges, and beaſts like Harts, vvith very long neckes, vvhich vvere afrayde of vs. Vpon the higheſt part of the hilles vve found ſome burying places, which were heapes of ſtones, and we not knowing what that meant, pulled the ſtones of from one of them, and vnder them found mens bones of 10 and 11 foote long, they buried the dead vpon the top of the hilles, flat on the ground, &amp; couer them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with ſtones, which keepes, them from being deuouered by beaſts or birdes.</p>
            <p>The 12.13.14.15. and 16. our men went continually on land to ſeeke for water, but found none, euery day bringing good ſtore of birdes and fiſhes on boord.</p>
            <p>The 17. We layd our ſhippe within the <hi>Kings Iſland</hi> on the wall, with a high water, to make it cleane, where it was drie that wee might goe round about it drie foot.</p>
            <p>The 18 the <hi>Horne</hi> was alſo layd on ſhore about 2 muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket ſhot from our ſhip, to make it cleane.</p>
            <p>The 19. as we were buſie about both the ſhips to make them cleane, and burnt reeds vnder the <hi>Horne,</hi> the flame of the fire ſodainly got into the ſhip, and preſently tooke ſuch hold thereof that in the twinckling of an eye, it was ſo great that wee could by no meanes quench it, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it lay 50. foot drie from the water ſide, and by that meanes we were conſtrained to ſtand ſtill, and ſee it burne
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17309:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>before our eyes, not able to doe any thing to ſaue it.</p>
            <p>The 20. at a high water we lancht the <hi>Vnitie,</hi> into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter againe, and went to the <hi>Horne</hi> &amp; quencht the fire, but the ſhip was burnt cleane downe to the water. The next day when we had caſt the water out of that part of it that was left, we ſaued all the wood, iron-worke, anchors, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and what elſe that was to be gotten and put it into ourſhip.</p>
            <p>The 25 our men found certaine hols full of freſh wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which was white and very thicke, from whence ſome of them daily fetch water, in litle rondlets on there ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſome went armed with muskets to defend them, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fetch birdes, &amp; egges, and young ſea Lyons which we eate, and are of a reaſonable good taſt. The ſea Lyons are a kind of fiſh, as big as a litle horſe, with heads like Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and long rough haire about their neckes, but the ſhe Lyons are without haire, and not halfe ſo great as the hee, we could not kill them but with muſket ſhot either in the breſt or the paunch, for though we gaue them 100. blowes with ſtaues and other things, and made the bloud run out of their mouthes and noſes, yet they would run away: while we lay there in the riuer, we had great windes and ſome times much raine, and ſtormes.</p>
            <p>The 9. of Ianuarie, 1616. we left fetching water into the ſhip, and the 10. wee ſet ſayle, to goe on our voiage, but the wind comming out of the ſea, we were forced to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor againe by the <hi>Lyon Iſland,</hi> and that day got great ſtore of fiſh and birdes.</p>
            <p>The 12 our <hi>Pinnace</hi> rowed to the <hi>Pinguijns Iſland,</hi> to fetch <hi>Pinguijns,</hi> but the weather was ſo foule, that they could not get a boord againe that day, but lay all night in the <hi>Smelt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bay</hi> and next morning came to vs laden with <hi>Pinguijns,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:17309:15"/>but by reaſon of the great number of them, they were ſpoyled, and we caſt them ouer boord.</p>
            <p>The 13 about noone, we ſailed out of <hi>Porto Deſire,</hi> but the ſea being calme we anchored before the hauen, and when the winde began to riſe, hoyſed anchor and put to ſea,</p>
            <p>The 18 we ſaw <hi>Sebaldes Iſlands</hi> ſouth eaſt from vs about 3. leagues, they lie, as <hi>Sebald Dewert</hi> writes, diſtant from the ſtraight, eaſt northeaſt, and weſt ſouthweſt, about 50. leagues, then we were vnder 51. degrees.</p>
            <p>The 20 vve ſaw <hi>Steencroſſe</hi> driue, and perceiued that we had a great ſtreame that went ſouthweſt, then vve vvere vnder 53 degrees, &amp; geſt that vve vvere about 20 leagues ſouth ward from the ſtraights of <hi>Magelan.</hi> The 11 vvee vvere vnder 53. degrees.</p>
            <p>The 23 in the morning vvee had a South vvinde, and about noone it vvaxt calme, then the vvinde blevv vveſt, and vve had ground at 50 fathom blacke ſandy, with ſmale ſtones, after that the winde turned north, with ſmooth water and faire weather, The vvater ſhewed as white as if wee had beene within the land, wee held our courſe ſouth and by weſt, about 3. of the clocke after noone we ſaw land weſt, and weſt ſouth weſt from vs, and not long after that vve ſavv it alſo in the ſouth, then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a north winde we went eaſt ſoutheaſt, to get aboue the land, it blew ſo hard in the hollow water, that wee were forced to take in our top ſayles.</p>
            <p>The 24. in the morning, wee ſaw land on ſtarre-boord not aboue a great league diſtant from vs, there wee had ground at 40. fathom, and a weſt winde, the land ſtrecht eaſt and ſouth, with very high hills, that were all couered ouer with ice. VVee ſayled along by that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17309:15"/>land, and about noone paſt it and ſaw other land caſt from it, which alſo was very high and ragged.</p>
            <p>Theſe lands as wee geſt lay about 8. leagues one from the other, and ſeemed as if there were a good paſſage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, which we were the better perſwaded vnto, for that there ran a hard ſtreame Southward betweene both thoſe lands.</p>
            <p>Then about noone wee were vnder 54 degrees 46. minutes and after noone wee had a north winde and made towards this opening, but about euening it calmed and that night we draue forwards with a hard ſtreame, and little winde. There we ſaw an innumerable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Pinguijns</hi> and thouſands of Whales, ſo that wee were forced to looke well about vs, and to wind and turne to ſhun the Whales, leaſt we ſhould ſayle vpon them.</p>
            <p>The 25 in the morning we were cloſe by the eaſt land, which was very high and craggy, which on the north ſide reacheth eaſt ſouth eaſt, as farre as wee could ſee, that land we called <hi>States land,</hi> but the land that lay weſt from vs, wee named <hi>Mauriceland.</hi> We perceiued that on both ſides thereof, there were good roades, and ſandy bayes, for on either ſide it had ſandy ſtrands and very faire ſandie ground. There are great ſtore of fiſh, <hi>Pinguijns</hi> and Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſſes, as alſo birdes and water enough, but we could ſee no trees, wee had a north winde in the entrie and went ſouth ſouthweſt, with a ſtife courſe, at noone wee were vnder 55 degrees 36 minutes, and then held our courſe ſouth weſt, with a good ſharpe winde and raine, and a ſtife gale: we ſavv the land on the ſouth ſide of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage vpon the vveſt ende of <hi>Maurice van Naſſawes land,</hi> reach vveſt ſouth vveſt and ſouth vveſt, as farre as wee could ſee it, all very high and craggie-land. In the euen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17309:16"/>the vvinde was South Weſt, and that night vvee went ſouth with great waues or billowes out of the ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vveſt, and very blew water, whereby wee iudged, and held for certaine that we had great deepe water to loef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from vs, nothing doubting but that it was the great South ſea, whereat we were exceeding glad, to thinke that wee had diſcouered a way, which vntill that time, was vnknowne to men, as afterward wee found it to be true.</p>
            <p>There we ſaw extreame great Sea-Mewes, bigger of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy then Swannes, their winges being ſpread abroad, were each of them aboue a fathom long. Theſe birds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnaccuſtomed to ſee men, came to our ſhip, and ſat thereon, and let our men take and kill them.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>map showing new passage through the great South Sea south of the Straits of Magellan in Tierra del Fuego</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17309:16"/>
            <p>The 26. we were vnder 57 degrees, with a flying ſtorme out of the Weſt and ſouth weſt, the whole quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with very high and blew water, vve held our courſe Southward, and in the north weſt ſaw very high land, in the night we turned north weſt ward.</p>
            <p>The 27 we were vnder 56. degrees 51, minutes, the weather very cold, with haile, and raine, the winde Weſt and Weſt and by ſouth, and we vvent Southward and then croſt northward with our maine ſailes.</p>
            <p>The 28 vvee hoyſed our top ſayles, then vvee had great billovves out of the Weſt, vvith a Weſt vvinde and then a northeaſt, and therewith held our courſe South, and then Weſt and Weſt and by South, and were vnder fiftie ſix degrees and fortie eight mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes.</p>
            <p>The 29, wee had a northeaſt vvinde, and held our courſe ſouth weſt and ſaw two Iſlands before vs, lying Weſt ſouthweſt from vs, about noone wee got to them but could not ſayle aboue them, ſo that wee held our courſe north, about them they had drie gray cliffes, and ſome low cliffes about them, they lay vnder 57 degrees, ſouthvvard of the equinoctiall line, vvee named them <hi>Barneuells Iſlands,</hi> from them we ſayled Weſt north weſt: about euening we ſaw land againe, lying north vveſt and north northweſt from vs, which was the land that lay South from the ſtraights of <hi>Magelan</hi> which reacheth Southward, all high hillie lande couered ouer with ſnow, ending with a ſharpe point, which wee called Cape <hi>Horne,</hi> it lyeth vnder 57. degrees and 48. minutes.</p>
            <p>Then vvee hadde faire weather, and a North vvinde, with great Billowes out of the Weſt, we held on
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17309:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>courſe weſt, &amp; found a ſtrong ſtreame that can weſtward.</p>
            <p>The 30. vve ſtill had great billovves out of the vveſt, vvith hollovv vvater and a ſtrong ſtreame that vvent vveſtvvard, vvhich aſſured vs that vvee had an open vvay into the South ſea, then vvee vvere vnder 57. degrees, 34. minutes.</p>
            <p>The 31. vve had a north vvinde, and ſayled vveſt, and vvere vnder 58. degrees: then the winde turning weſt, and weſt ſouthweſt, ſomewhat variable, we paſſed by Cape <hi>Van Horne,</hi> and could ſee no more land, and had great billowes out of the weſt, and very blew vvater, vvhich then fully aſſured vs that vve had the broad ſouth ſea before vs, and no land: the vvind vvas very variable vvith greate ſtore of hayle and raine, vvhich forced vs of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times to vvinde to and fro.</p>
            <p>The firſt of February, vvee had cold vveather, vvith a ſtorme out of the South-vveſt, and ſayled vvith our maine ſayles, lying northvveſt and vveſt northvveſt.</p>
            <p>The 2. the vvinde vveſt, vvee ſayled ſouthvvard, and vvere vnder 57. degrees 58. minutes, and found 12. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees Northvvarde variation of the Compaſſe. That day vve ſavv many great Sea-mevves, and other birds.</p>
            <p>The 3. wee were vnder 59. degrees 25. minutes, with indifferent weather, and a hard weſt winde, and geſſed that we were that day vnder 59. degrees and a halfe, but ſaw no land, nor any ſigne thereof in the South.</p>
            <p>The 4. we were vnder 56. degrees 43. minutes, with variable windes, moſt ſouthweſt, and wound to and fro as the wind blew, with 11. degrees northeaſtward varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Compaſſe.</p>
            <p>The 5. wee had a ſtrong ſtreame out of the weſt, with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17309:17"/>hollow water, whereby wee could beare no ſayle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut were forced to driue with the winde.</p>
            <p>The 8. the winde was ſouth, and wee held weſt, and the winde blowing northweſt, we turned ſouthward, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnder 59. degrees, little leſſe: the wind being ſtiffe northweſt and north northweſt, with miſt, colde, hayle, and ſnow, vvee had our maine ſayles out, and held our courſe weſt.</p>
            <p>The next day, it was very cold, raw, moiſt and miſtie vveather.</p>
            <p>The 12. our men had each of them three cups of vvine in ſigne of ioy for our good hap, for then the Sraightes of <hi>Magelan</hi> lay eaſt from vs: the ſame day by aduice of all our counſell, at the requeſt of our chiefe Marchant, the new paſſage (by vs diſcouered betweene <hi>Mauritius</hi> land and the <hi>States</hi> land,) was named the <hi>Straights</hi> of <hi>le Maire,</hi> although by good right it ſhould rather haue bin called <hi>William Schoutens Straight,</hi> after our Maiſters Name, by whoſe wiſe conduction and skill in ſayling, the ſame was found.</p>
            <p>During the time that wee paſſed through that Nevv Straight, and ſayling ſouthward about that New found land, till we got to the Weſt ſide of the Straights of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelan</hi> for the moſt part we had a very ſtrong ſtreame, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vvater, continuall raine, miſts, moiſt and thicke wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with much hayle and ſnow: whereby wee endured much trouble, miſery and diſeaſe. But in regard that we had ſo luckily diſcouered that Paſſage, and hoping that the places which we were yet to diſcouer would likewiſe fall out well; wee were encouraged, not once thinking vpon our former hard paſſage, with aſſured mindes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to goe forward on our voyage.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:17309:18"/>
            <p>The 13. we ſtill had much raine and miſty darke wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſaw many birds and Porpeſſes.</p>
            <p>The 14. We were vnder 51. degrees 50. minutes, with miſty darke and moiſt weather, as alſo the 15. but ſlight water, being vnder 51. degrees 12. minutes, the winde Weſt, holding our courſe north, and found that the ſtreame there, ran north.</p>
            <p>The next, the wind ſtill held northweſt, north north<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt, and weſt, to the 23. day, then we had the generall South winde, and good weather, with hollow billowes out of the ſouthweſt and were vnder 46. degrees and 30. minutes,</p>
            <p>The 24. Wee hoyſed our vpper Ordinance out of the hold, and placed it aboue vpon our decke.</p>
            <p>The 25. of Ianuary, vve hoyſed all our ſayles, becauſe we entered into a peaceable Sea, and had paſt all ſtormes and hard weather.</p>
            <p>The 27. We hoyſed vp our ſecond tyre of Ordinance, and placed it in our ſecond Orlope, for in <hi>Porto Deſire</hi> wee had layd it downe in the hold, and all thinges that might hinder the wind, and then were vnder 40. degrees with faire weather, a ſouth, and ſouth ſoutheaſt winde, and a good gale, as the day before, and held our courſe northward.</p>
            <p>The 28. our counſell and the foure Maſters determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſayle to the Iſles of <hi>Iohn Fernando,</hi> there to refreſh vs, becauſe ſome of our men by meanes of the great paines and labour taken by them were extreame weary, and ſome had the flux: that day wee were vnder 35. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 53. minutes. In the euening wee bare but ſmall ſayle, fearing to fall vpon the land by night, and becauſe we would not paſſe bey ond it in the night, vvee ſayled
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17309:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>northeaſt.</p>
            <p>The firſt of March in the morning we ſaw the Iſlands of <hi>Iohn Fernando,</hi> right before vs, north northeaſt, with a ſouth winde, faire weather, and a good gale. About noone wee got to them, vnder 33. degrees and 48. minutes.</p>
            <p>Theſe are two Iſlands, both of them very high land: the ſmalleſt lying moſt weſtward, is a very dry bare Iſland with nothing in it, but bare hilles and cliffes, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt (lying eaſtward) is alſo full of very high hilles, but hath many trees, and very fruitfull. Therein are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny beaſtes, as hogges, and goates, vpon the coaſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable numbers of good fiſh; which makes the <hi>Spanyards</hi> often times come thither to fiſh, and in ſhort time fill their ſhips and carry them to <hi>Peru.</hi> We went on the weſt ſide of thoſe Iſlandes, which was not well for vs, for there we muſt haue gone about eaſtward to get into the Road, which lyeth on the eaſt point of the greateſt Iſland, for going about on the weſt ſide behind the land, we ſhould haue gotten vnder the land in the calme water, becauſe the land there is high and calme, ſo that we could not get to the land to anchor with our ſhippe, and therefore ſent our boate out to ſound the depth, which came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord againe in the the euening, and told vs, that cloſe by the land wee had 40. and 30, fathome ſandy ground, which ſtill leſſeneth till it come to 3. fathom good to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor in, beſides a faire greene valley, full of greene trees, pleaſant to behold, but becauſe of the ſhortneſſe of the time they went not on ſhore, and in diuers places ſaw freſh water in great ſtreames run downe off the hils, they likewiſe ſaw many goates and other beaſts vpon the hils, which they could not well know, being ſo farre off: they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17309:19"/>had alſo in ſhort time taken a great number of good fiſh, for the hooke was no ſooner in the water but preſently they tooke fiſh, ſo that continually without ceaſing, they did nothing but draw vp fiſh, moſt of them being Corco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bados, and Steenbraſſes, and ſaw many ſea Wolues: theſe newes cheared vp our men, ſpecially thoſe that were troubled with looſeneſſe hoping there to refreſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: that night it was calme weather, ſo that the ſtreame draue vs ſomewhat backeward.</p>
            <p>The 2. day we were with our ſhip cloſe vnder the land againe, but could not get ſo neere (what meanes ſoeuer we vſed) to finde ground, wee once againe ſent our men on land, ſome to fiſh, and ſome to ſeeke for cattell, they ſaw many hogs, goates, and other beaſtes, but by reaſon that the woods were thicke they could not get them: and the while that ſome of them fetcht water, they that were in the boate had taken almoſt two tunnes of fiſh, all with hookes, and ſo we were forced to leaue that faire Iſland, and could get nothing elſe there.</p>
            <p>The 3. we draue at leaſt 4. leagues beneath the Iſlands, notwithſtanding that all that quarter we did the beſt vve could to ſaile neere to it, vvhereof at laſt being vvearie, (ſeing it vvas vnpoſſible to be done) vve determined to leaue them, and to hold on our courſe, to performe our voyage, euery day hauing a good fore-vvinde, to the great griefe of our ſicke men, vvho thereby vvere cleane out of comfort, but God holpe them.</p>
            <p>Theſe Iſlands are vnder 33. degrees 40. minutes: this reſolution taken, vvee ſet our courſe northvveſt and by Weſt, vvith a good South gale of vvinde, and fayre vvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The 11. vve paſt <hi>Tropicus Capricornus</hi> the ſecond time,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17309:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>vvith a ſouth eaſt vvinde, our courſe northvveſt, there vve had the generall eaſt and eaſt ſoutheaſt vvinde, and held our courſe north north vveſt to the 15. till we were vnder 18. degrees, then vve changed our courſe, and went vveſt, and made our rovving Shullop ready, to vſe it vvhen vve came neere any land.</p>
            <p>The 17. vve vvere vnder 19. degrees, and held our courſe Weſt northvveſt.</p>
            <p>The 20. vve vvere vnder 17 degrees, vvith very high bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovves out of the ſouth, the vvinde ſoutheaſt as before, we held our courſe Weſt northvveſt, our Compaſſe then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing halfe a Strike variation north weſtward, euery day we ſaw many Pilſters, &amp; other birds, Pilſters are white birds, with red billes, and reddiſh heads, and long white clouen tayles, of two or two foote and a halfe long, they are to be ſeene in all parts of the world, whereſoeuer we ſayle, and are as big as a common Sea mew.</p>
            <p>The 24. we were vnder 15. degrees, and held our courſe weſt, euery day hauing hollow billowes out of the ſouth, and continuall ſtiffe cold winde eaſt ſouthe aſt, and ſtill went forward, with a good gale.</p>
            <p>The 3. of Aprill being Eaſter day, we vvere vnder 15. degrees 12. minutes, at vvhich time vve had no variation of Compaſſe, for the needle ſtood right north and ſouth, then the flux began much to trouble our men, for at times, halfe of them at the leaſt had it.</p>
            <p>The 9. <hi>Iohn Cornelius Schouten</hi> that had beene Maſter of the <hi>Horne, (William Cornelius Schoutens</hi> Brother, our Maſter) died, when he had lyen ſicke a moneth.</p>
            <p>The 10. In the morning after vve had prayed, his dead body vvas throvvne ouer boord, and preſently after vvee ſavv land northvveſt and northvveſt and by north, about
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17309:20"/>three leagues from vs, a low Iſland, not very great, there alſo wee ſaw great numbers of Sea-mewes and fiſh, and ſet our courſe to the Iſland, thinking to haue ſome refreſhing, whereof in regard of the flux wee had great neede. About noone wee got to the Iſland, and caſt out our lead, but found no ground, and therefore put out our Shalop, to ſee if we could finde any ground, the Shalop returning, they told vs that they found ground at 25. fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom about a ſmall musket ſhot from the land, they ſayd alſo that they had ſeene many Hayes and other fiſh, ſuch as we found about <hi>Iohn Fernandos</hi> Iſlands, but we durſt not goe with our ſhip ſo cloſe vnder the land, fearing ſome danger. Then our Shalop went to the land againe to ſee what they might get there, but comming neere to the Iſland they could not get to the ſtrand with the ſhalop the water ruſht ſo hard againſt the ſhore, which our men perceiuing, leapt into the water and ſwam, and drew one another to land, leauing the ſhalop faſt with a drag, about euening they came on boord againe, and could get no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but onely ſome greene he arbes, which taſted like vnto <hi>Holland</hi> Tuinkars, they ſaid, that there they had ſeene three Dogs, that neither barkt, nor made any noyſe, and in it found ſome places full of raine water, that had fallen that day.</p>
            <p>The Iſland as wee perceiued, ſeemed at high water for the moſt part to be ouerflowne, it had nothing about it but a kinde of wall like a ditch, full of greene trees, pleaſant to behold, and in the middle of them and elſe where, much ſalt water. It is vnder 15. degrees twelue minutes, diſtant from the Coaſt of <hi>Peru</hi> by our eſtimation nine hundred twenty &amp; fiue leagues. That quarter the winde was North, and wee held our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17309:20"/>courſe Weſt, to wards the Iſlands of <hi>Salomon,</hi> and called that Iſland <hi>Dogs Iſland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the night it blewer hard, with a great ſhowre of raine.</p>
            <p>The 14. the winde eaſt and eaſt ſoutheaſt, wee ſayled Weſt and weſt and by north, with winde and weather a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayd, and ſaw much fiſh, and many birdes: after noone vve ſaw another low Iſland North vveſt from vs being very great, and reached northeaſt and ſouthvveſt, wherat vvee reioyced, hoping to get vvater and ſome refreſhing there, and made to it, holding our courſe northweſt.</p>
            <p>About euening, being with our ſhip about a league from the land, there came a Canoe to meete vs, with 4. <hi>Indians</hi> in it, al naked, of a reddiſh colour, very black long haire: they kept a good way from our ſhip firſt calling to vs, making ſignes to haue vs come on land, but we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood them not, nor they vs, not withſtanding that we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvered and called to them in <hi>Spaniſh, Molucus, Iauan,</hi> and our owne <hi>Netherland</hi> ſpeech.</p>
            <p>About euening at Sunne-ſetting, we got to the land, but found no ground, nor no changing of water, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we were ſo neere to the ſhore, that with a musket we might ſhoote into it, and therefore put to Sea againe, and the Canoe to land, vvhere a great many <hi>Indians</hi> ſtood vpon the ſhore to watch for them: not long after againe there came another Canoe from the Land to our ſhippe, but would not (as the firſt) come aboord, they called to vs, and vvee to them, but vnderſtoode not one the other, at laſt their Canoe ouerthrewe in the water, but they ſoone turned it vp againe, and leapt quickely into it, they ſhevved and pointed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17309:21"/>to wards the land, and wee the like to them towards the ſhippe, but they would not come, wherewith we held on our courſe and left the Iſland, ſayling South and ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt to get aboue the land: the Iſland was not broad, but ſomewhat long, and full of trees, which as wee geſſed were Palmitas and Cocus trees, it lies vnder 15. degrees 15. minutes, hauing white ſand ground, that night wee ſaw fire vpon the land in diuers places.</p>
            <p>The 15. in the morning, hauing in the night ſayled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ten leagues ſouth ſouthweſt, wee ſayled cloſe along by the land, where we ſaw many naked men ſtanding on ſhore, calling and crying (as it ſeemed) to bid vs come on land, and then again there came another Canoe from the land towards our ſhip, with three Indians in it, which alſo called to vs, and would not come aboord, but rowed to the Shalop, and went cloſe to it, our men ſhewing them all the friendſhip they could, giuing them ſome beades and kniues, but they vnderſtood not one another hauing beene a little while by the Shalop, they left it, and came ſo neere to our ſhippe, that we caſt out a ſmall rope to them, which they tooke, but would not enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſhip, but went into the Shalop, which came backe from the land without doing any thing, and hauing bin a good while in it, at the laſt one of them came into the gallerie, and drew our the nayles of the windowes in the marchants and Maſters Cabines, and taking them away, hid them in his haire, they were deſirous of Iron, for they ventured to pull out the bolts with their hands, and to earry them away, we ſought to keepe one of them in the ſhip and to ſend one of our men with the other two in their Cano to land to make friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe with them but they would not, they were very
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17309:21"/>theeuiſh people, all naked, only a peece of a mat hanging before their priuie members. Their ſkin was marked with diuers figures, as Snakes, Dragons, and ſuch like things vvhich ſhewed very blew, as if they had bin burnt thereon with gun-powder, we gaue them wine, as they ſat in the Canoe, but they would not giue vs the cup againe. We ſent our Shalop once againe to the land, vvith 8. muſketiers, and 6. men vvith ſvvords <hi>Claus Iohnſon</hi> our vnder Marchant, and <hi>Arice Clauſon</hi> the Marchant of the <hi>Horne,</hi> vvent vvith them, to ſee vvhat vvas to be gotten in the Iſland, and to make friendſhip vvith them. But as ſoone as they vvere by the ſtrand and the men vvent on ſhore, there came at leaſt 30 <hi>Indians</hi> out of the vvood vvith great Clubs or Cudgels and vvould haue taken our mens armes from them and thought to dravv the Shalop vpon the land, ventred to take tvvo of our men out of the Shalop, thinking to carrie them into the vvood, but our muſketiers, hauing their muſkets ready, diſcharged three of them amongſt them, and verily thought that they either killed or ſore vvounded ſome of them. They likevviſe hadde long ſtaues, vvith very long ſharpe things at the endes thereof, vvhich (as vvee thought) vvere ſinnes of blacke fiſhes, they alſo caſt ſtones vvith ſtings, but (God be thanked) hurt none of our men, bowes they hadde not, as farre as wee could ſee. Our men ſaw ſome of their women, that cryed and claſpt their men about the neckes, but knew not vvhat they meant, but thought they did it to get them from thence. That Iſland (by reaſon wee could there finde no ground to anchor) we called the Iſland without ground. On the out ſide it was low plaine ground, full of palme trees, but within full of ſalt water.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17309:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>At laſt when wee ſaw that there was nothing to be gotten we determined to leaue it, and with an eaſt vvinde held our courſe VVeſt to ſeaward. There we had ſlight wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and no billowes as the day before we had out of the South, and therefore we geſt that Southward there was more land, it is vnder 15 degrees, about 100 leagues diſtant from <hi>Dogs Iland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 16. in the morning betimes, wee ſaw an other Iſland, North ward from vs, which we made to, but found it as the other, without anchor ground, within alſo being all drowned land, yet on the ſids it was full of trees, but no plume nor Cocos trees. Wee put out our Shalop to ſound the depth, but, going to the ſhore, found no ground, and therefore came a boorde againe, without doeing any thing, or ſeeing any men. Wee ſent our Shalop once againe to ſee if we could get any refreſhing or water vpon the land, who returning againe tolde vs that they hadde found freſh water not farre from the ſhore, in a pit or keele, which they might bring with buckets to the ſtrand, but hard to get into the ſhippe, for the Shalop, by reaſon of the billowes, lay faſt at a dreg, by which meanes the men were forced, to draw one an other vvith a rope on land, and in like ſort on boorde againe, ſo that it was very troubleſome and dangerous to goe on the land, and therefore fetcht but foure ſmall fats of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. There alſo vvee found ſuch herbes as vvee hadde in the <hi>Dogs Iſland,</hi> vvhereof vve brought a ſackefull a boorde, and ſome crabs as alſo ſome ſhels, and hornes, that had fiſh in them of very good taſt, That euening we held on our courſe Weſtward, with an eaſt winde, and an in different gale, rainie weather and ſmoth water.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17309:22"/>The ſame day wee were vnder 14. degrees 46. minutes. That Iſland was 15. leagues diſtant from the other, we cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it the water Iſland, by cauſe there we got ſome water.</p>
            <p>The 17. wee gaue our men ſix cups of water, and ſod a great ketle with pottage made of the greene herbes that wee had in water Iſland, which did our men ſome good and eaſed them of their looſeneſſe.</p>
            <p>The 18. in the morning, wee ſaw an other low Iſland ſouth weſt from vs, lying Weſt north weſt, and eaſt ſouth eaſt, as farre as wee could ſee, at the leaſt twentie leagues, diſtant from the other. Wee made to it, and being hard by it, ſent out our boate to sound the depth they told vs they found ground by a point of land, from whence there came a ſtreame at twentie, twentie fiue and fortie fathom, running ſoftly downe, about a muſket ſhot from the land, whereupon wee ſent the boate with our emptie caſke thither, hoping to finde vvater. When it came to the land, they let the Schut lie faſt at a dreg in the water and drew one an other with a rope though the water, to land as they did before, there they ſought a good vvay vvithin a vvood for freſh vvater, but becauſe they had no armes with them, and ſavv a vvilde man, vvho as they thought had a bovv in his hand, they turned preſently backe to the Shalop, and came aboord againe vvithout doing any thing, and lying a good vvay from the ſhoare, there came fiue or ſix vvild men to the ſtrand, vvho ſeeing that our men were gon, went backe againe into the wood. Vpon that Iſland there were great ſtore of greene wild trees, being alſo full of ſalt water with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. When our men came into the ſhippe they were couered all ouer vvith flies, in ſuch abundance that we
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17309:23"/>could not know them, their faces, hands, and Scute and all full, and the owers alſo as farre as they were out of the water, were couered ouer with blacke flies, wonderfull to behold: thoſe flies came with them aboord our ſhip and flue ſo thicke vpon our bodies and in our faces, that vve knew not how to ſhun them, for wee could hardly eate or drinke, but all was full of them: vve ſtill wipt our faces and hands, and made flaps to kill as many as wee could, this continued two or three dayes with great trouble vnto vs all: at laſt wee had a good gale of winde, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and with continuall killing them, in the ende when three or four dayes were paſt we were rid of them, wee called that Iſland, the <hi>Flie Iſland,</hi> and therewith ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from it, and had ſome raine, as alſo the next day, whereby wee gathered ſo much water, with clothes and ſayles that it holpe vs well, in the night wee made no great way but often times let the ſhip driue, that wee might not by night fall vpon ſuch low Iſlands, and ſpoyle our ſhip.</p>
            <p>The 23. wee were vnder 15. degrees 4. minutes, and then againe had great hollow bill ovves out of flie ſouth, which the next day alſo continued, the winde vvas north eaſt and moſt part eaſt, and eaſt and by ſouth. There they ſayd that <hi>Terra Auſtralis</hi> which we ſought for, lay yet 250. leagues further.</p>
            <p>The 25. wee filled foure veſſells full of raine water; and ſtill had hollow billowes out of the ſouth, as we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly haue in the <hi>Spaniſh ſeas</hi> out of the north weſt.</p>
            <p>The 3. of May the winde was ſtill eaſt, and wee ſay led Weſt, and at woone were vnder 15 degrees, 3 minutes, That day we ſaw many great Dorados which were the firſt that wee had ſeene in the ſouth ſea.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:17309:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The 9. Wee were vnder 15. degrees 20. minutes, and at that time as wee thought were 1510. leagues diſtant from the coaſt of <hi>Peru</hi> and <hi>Chili.</hi> About noone wee ſaw a ſayle, which as wee geſſed was a Barke, comming out of the ſouth, and went northward towards vs, we preſently made towards it, and as it came neere to vs, wee ſhot at it with one of our peeces right ouer her, to make them ſtrike, but they would not, then wee ſhot againe, but yet they would not ſtrike, with that we put out our Shalop with 10. musketiers in it, to take her, which calling to them wee ſhot another peece, yet without any intent to reach or to hurt them, but they would not ſtrike, but ſought as well as they could to get away from vs, and got to loofeward of vs, but our Shalop being too crafty for them rowed to them, and being about halfe a musket ſhot from them ſhot foure muskets one after an other, as they drew neere to her, and before they could reach her ſome of her men in great feare leapt ouerboord, whereof one of them had a little child, and another was hurt, and had three holes in his backe, but not very deepe, for it was hayleſhot, thoſe we fetcht out of the water a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: they alſo threw much of their goods ouer boord, and amongſt the reſt three Hennes, our men leapt into their ſhip, and carryed them into our ſhip, they not once reſiſting, for in truth they had no armes, when they were in our ſhip we fetcht two men more that were left in theirs, which preſently fell downe before vs, and kiſt our feete and hands, one of them was a very old man, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a young man, wee could not vnderſtand them, but vſed them kindely, and preſently the Shalop rowd to fetch thoſe that leapt ouerboord, to ſaue their liues, but they gotte but two of them, that droue vpon one of their oares, and pointed to our men
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17309:24"/>with their hands to the ground, as much to ſay, that the reſt were drownd: one of thoſe two that was hurt, whom wee dreſt, had long yealowiſh haire. In that ſhippe there was at leaſt eight women, three young ſucking children, and ſome of nine or ten yeares old, ſo that we made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they were three and twentie in all, cleane naked prople, both men and women, onely ſomething han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging before their priuie members. About euening vvee ſet the men on boord their ſhippe againe, that were wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to their wiues, which claſpt them about the necks and kiſt them. Wee gaue them beades, (which they hung about their neckes,) and ſome kniues, and ſhewed them all the friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hip we could, and they the like to vs, giuing vs two fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Matiens, and two Cocos nuts, for they had not many, that was all they had to eate and drinke, and they had drunke out all the vvater out of the nuttes, ſo that they had no more drinke. Wee ſaw them drinke ſalt vvater out of the Sea, and gaue it alſo to their young children, to drinke, which vvee thought to bee againſt Nature. They had certaine clothes, vvhich they vvare before their priuie mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and therevvith couered themſelues againſt the heate of the Sunne, of a yealowiſh colour. They vvere reddiſh people, that annoynted themſelues with Oyle: the Women had ſhort hayre, like our men in <hi>Holland:</hi> Mens hayre vvas long, curled, and very blacke: their ſhip was of a ſtrang faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: It was made of 2. long faire Canoes with a good ſpace betweene them, in each Canoe about the middle thereof, there lay two whole broad planckes of fayre redde vvood, to keepe out the vvater, and diuers planckes layd croſſe ouer, from the one Canoe to the other, which were made faſt together, and hung
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17309:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>a good way ouer on both endes, without the Canoes, very cloſe aboue to keepe out the water, before at the ende of one of the Canoes, on ſtarre-boord, there ſtood a Maſt, at the end thereof hauing a forke, whereon the yard lay. The ſayle vvas made of mats, and as the vvinde blovve they ſayled, without Compaſſe, or any Inſtruments for the Sea, but hookes to fiſh withall, whereof the vpper part was ſtone, the other blacke bone, or Torroyſes ſhelles, and ſome of them vvere mother of pearle. Their ropes were very fayre, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as thicke as a Cable, made of ſuch ſtuffe as the figge frayles in <hi>Spayne</hi> are. When they ſayled from vs, they hold their courſe ſoutheaſt.</p>
            <p>The tenth, We had the vvinde South ſoutheaſt, and ſoutheaſt and by South, and held our courſe Weſt, and ſouthweſt In the morning after breakefaſt, we ſaw very high land on backeboord, lying Southeaſt and by ſouth, about eight leagues from vs: vve made to it, and ſayled all that day with a good gale, but could not reach it, and therefore held off in the night, in the euening wee ſaw a ſayle a great may beneath the land, and preſently after another alſo, a great deale be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low they often wound to and fro and in the night they made fires, and drew neere one vnto the other.</p>
            <p>The eleuenth in the morning, wee vvere neere a high Iſland, and about tvvo Leagues ſouthvvard from thence, an other long low Iſland, that day vvee ſayled ouer a banke of foureteene fathome deepe, ſtony ground, lying about tvvo Leagues from the land, and as ſoone as wee were ouer it, wee could finde no more grounde. One of the Shippes aforeſaid came to vs, and wee caſt out a rope at our ſterne think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17309:25"/>they would take it, and draw themſelues by is aboord our ſhippe, but they could not gette it till one of our men leapt ouer boord, and holp them to take it, which they vntyed, and tooke it into their ſhippe, and tyed two Cocos nuts, and 3 or 4 flying fiſhes to the rope, and ſo let it go calling aloud to vs, but we could not vnderſtand them, but we thought their meaning was, that we ſhould pull the rope on boord againe: they alſo carry a Canoe in their ſhip, which what time ſoeuer, they can put out: and are very good Sea men. Their ſhips were of the faſhion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoreſayd, with good ſayles, and are ſo ſwift of ſayle, that few ſhips in <hi>Holland</hi> can out ſayle them. They ſteere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind with 2. oares, on each Canoe a man, &amp; ſometimes row, with their oares before, when they will wind, the ſhip alſo windes of it ſelfe, when they pull the oates out of the water and let it goe, or alone with the winde, vvee put out our Shalop to ſound, vvhich came and told vs that they had found ground at 15.14. and 12. fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thome, ſheluie ground, about a canon ſhot from the land, wee preſently made to it to anchor, and tooke in our ſayles. The <hi>Negroes</hi> ſeeing that, made fignes to vs to goe to the other Iſland, and ſayled thither before vs, but wee anchored at the ende of the Iſland, at fiue and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie fathome ſandie ground, a great Cannon ſhot from the land. That Iſland is a high hill, almoſt like one of the <hi>Molucos</hi> Iſlandes, full of trees, moſt Cocos trees, therefore wee called it <hi>Cocos</hi> Iſland.</p>
            <p>The other Iſland is much longer, but lower, lying Eaſt and Weſt. As ſoone as wee were at an anchor, there came three ſmall ſhippes, that ſayled vp and dovvne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout our ſhippe, and at leaſt nine or ten Canoes boorded vs, ſome from the lande, and ſome out of the little ſhippes, among the which, tvvo of them put
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17309:25"/>out litle white flags in ſigne of peace, and wee did the like. Their Canoes, which had 3. and 4. men a peece in them, vvere flat before and ſharpe behinde, hewed out of a whole peece of reed wood. Wherewith they could row exceeding ſwift, and when they came neere the ſhip, they leapt into the water, and ſwam to our ſhip, with their hands full of Cocos nuttes, and Vbes rootes, which they bartred vvith vs for nayles and beades, whereof they were very deſirous, they gaue foure or fiue Cocos nutts, for one naile or a ſmall ſtring of beades, ſo that the ſame day wee bartered for 180. Cocos nuttes, and at laſt there came ſo many on boord, that wee ſcarſe knew how to beſtirre our ſelues. We ſent our Shalop towards the other Iſland, to ſee if there vve could not lie better, for there we lay in the open ſea, but the Shalop was no ſooner off from our ſhip, rowing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long by the land, but it was encloſed round about by 12 or 13. Canoes of the other Iſland, and ſtill more came to them, the people within them ſhewing as if they vvere mad, hauing certaine ſtaues of hard wood in their hands, like Clubs, ſharpe at the point, and a litle burnt. They boorded our Shalop, and thought to haue taken it from vs, but our men being thereby conſtrained to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelues, let flee three muſkets among them, whereat firſt they laught and mockt, thinking it but a ſport, but the third time one of them was ſhot into the breſt cleane through his body, which his fellowes ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing went preſently to helpe him, and finding him to be ſo ſore hurt, all of them kept of from the Shalop, and went to one of their ſmall ſhippes with ſayles, and calling to it would haue hadde them to ouer row the Shalop, as wee geſt, but they would not, for their Canoes had bin aboord our ſhip, where they had beene well vſed, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17309:26"/>friendly delt with all. Thoſe people were very theeuiſh, for in our ſight they ſtole one of our leads wherewith our men vſed to ſound, and whatſoeuer they ſaw, they would ſteale and ſwim away with it as ſome of them did. that ſtole avvay one of our mens pillovves and couerlet. others tooke kniues and vvhat elſe they could finde. Wherevvith they preſently leapt ouer boorde, and ſvvam avvay, ſo that in the night vvee vvere forſt to take in our Shalop, leaſt they ſhould cut the rope, and carrie it avvay, they vvere exceeding deſirous of iron, looking round about vpon the nayles and bolts of the ſhippe, thinking to pull them out and to ſteale them avvay, but they vvere to faſt in the vvood. They vvere luſty men vvell proportioned, and of great ſtature, and vvent all naked and vnarmed onely their priuie members coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Their haire vvas dreſt after diuers faſhions, ſome ſhort and ſome finely curled, ſome had long haire bound vp in plaits in ſeuerall manner, they vvere notable ſvvim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers. That <hi>Cocos Iſland</hi> lyes vnder 16 degrees 10 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes. The twelfe in the morning after breake-faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, there came more Canoes a boorde our ſhip with Cocos nuts, Bananas, Vbas rootes, and ſome litle hogs, and ſome veſſels full of freſh vvater, that day vvee bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered vvith them for one thouſand two hundred Cocos nuts, vvee vvere 85. men aboord and euery one had tvvelue nuts. They stroue vvho ſhould get firſt aboord and thoſe that could not get to the ſhippe, leapt out of their Canoes, and diued vnder the other Canoes, to get to the ſhippe to ſell their vvare, holding Vbas rootes, and bunches of Cocos nuts in their mouthes, and climed ſo many, and ſo faſt vp to the ſhippe, that vvee vvere forced to keepe them downe with ſtaues. When they had ſold their wares, they leapt out of the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17309:26"/>ſhip and ſwam to their Canoes againe. They won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at the greatneſſe and ſtrength of the ſhippe, and ſome of them crept downe behinde at the rother, vnder the ſhippe, and knockt with ſtones vpon the bottome th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reof, to proue how ſtrong it was. There came a Canoe from the other Iſland, that brought vs a young black wilde hog, which the king ſent vs for a preſent, wee vvould haue giuen the meſſenger ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for it, but he would not take it, making ſignes that the king hadde charged him not to take any thing. At noone the king himſelfe came in a great ſhippe with a ſayle, of the faſhion aforeſayd, like an Ice Slead, with at leaſt thirtie fiue Canoes to accompany him. This king was by his men called <hi>Latou,</hi> wee receiued him with Drummes and Trumpets, where at they wondred, becauſe they neuer hadde ſcene nor heard the like before, They ſhewed vs great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and much friendſhip outwardly, with bowing their heades, clapping their fiſts together ouer their heads and other ſtrange ceremonies. When hee was a litle way from vs hee beganne to call and to crie out alowd, as if hee hadde prayed after his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, all the reſt of his men did the like, vvee not knowing what it ment, but geſt that it was in ſteed of a welcome.</p>
            <p>Preſently thereupon the king ſent vs a <hi>Matien</hi> by three of his men, to whom wee gaue an old hatcher, a few beades, ſome old nayles, and a peece of linnen cloth, which hee willingly receiued, laying it three times vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his head, and bowing it, in token of reuerence, or thankes, and curteſie. Thoſe that came into our ſhip, fell on their knees, and kiſt our feet, and wondred much at our ſhippe. Wee could not know the king
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17309:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>from the other Indians, for he was likewiſe cleane naked, but onely that they ſhewed him reuerence, and hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded ouer his men. Wee made ſignes that the king ſhould come aboord of our ſhip, his ſonne came aboord, and wee intertained him well, but he himſelfe durſt not, or would not come, but they altogether made ſignes to haue vs come to the further Iſland, with our ſhip, where there was enough of all things to be had. Among other things we bartered with them for angles of haire, that were made of reed, as in <hi>Holland,</hi> but ſome what thicker, with hookes of mother of Pearle. The kings ſonne went to land againe, and the Canoe where in he went had a great peece of wood on backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord, wherewith it kept vpright, vpon that peece of wood their angle lay, ready to take fiſh.</p>
            <p>The 13. in the morning, there came at leaſt 45. Canoes aboord, to trafficke with vs, with an armado of 23. ſmall ſhippes, made like ice ſleads, each of them one with an other, hauing 25 men a peece in them, and euery ſmall Canoe 4 or 5 we not knowing what their intent was. The Canoes deait with vs bartering Cocos nuttes, for nayles, and made ſhow, as if they were our great friends, but afterward we found it otherwiſe: all of them made ſignes to vs to ſayle to the other Iſland, the king who the day before had beene at our ſhippe, came likewiſe in his ſhippe with a ſayle to our ſhip, and all of them made a great noyſe. Wee would gladly haue hadde him aboorde, but he would not, where with we ſuſpected treaſon fearing ſome miſchiefe, and the rather, becauſe all the ſhippes and Canoes kept cloſe round about our ſhip, and that the king went out of his ſhip into a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noe, and his ſonne into an other, and preſently they ſtroke vpon a kinde of drumme that was in his ſhippe,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17309:27"/>whereat all the <hi>Indians</hi> began to crie out alowd, which we eſteemed to be a warning giuen vnto them, altogether to fall vpon vs, to take our ſhippe from vs, and then the ſhip wherein the king ſayled before hee went out of it, boorded vs, comming ſo hard vpon vs, as if it would haue ſuncke vs, but it ſtrucke againſt our ſhip with ſuch a force that the two heads of the Canoes before brake in peeces, wherewith the men that were in it, (among them hauing ſome women) leapt into the water and ſwam to wind ward, the reſt began to fling great number of ſtones at vs thinking therewith to feare vs, but we ſhot at them with muſkets and 3 great peeces (laden with muſket ſhot and old nayles) wherewith all they that were in the ſhip and Canoes that lay about our ſhip, leapt into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, we made reckoning that ſome of them hadde forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the way to goe home againe, and that diuers of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>o were ſore wounded, and therewith they went backe: they knew not what ſuch manner of ſhooting ment, but yet when they ſaw how we had handled them with our ſhot, they kept aloofe out of the reach of our peeces, and wee hoyſing anchor, ſet forward againe on our voyage, holding our courſe weſt, and weſt and by ſouth. VVee were of opinion that the king at that time, hadde aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled all his forces, for he had at the leaſt 1000. men, or rather more, among them wee ſaw one that was cleane white.</p>
            <p>When wee were about foure leagues off from the Iſlands, many of our men would haue had vs goe backe againe to the Iſlands, by force to goe on land, to refreſh our ſelues, in regarde that wee had but litle water, but the maſter and the Marchant would not. The firſt Iſland that was ſo high, wee named Cocos Iſland, and the other that lay a league diſtant from it, wee called <hi>Traitors</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17309:28"/>Iſland, becauſe the moſt part of the <hi>Indians</hi> that ſought to betray vs, came from that Iſland.</p>
            <p>The 14. in the morning, we ſaw another Iſland right before vs, about ſeuen Leagues diſtant from vs, which ſeemed to be round, and as wee geſt was thirty Leagues diſtant from the Iſlandas, foreſaid. That Iſland vvee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Hope,</hi> and made towards it, hoping there to gette water, and better refreſhing, but comming to it, could find no ground, and therefore put out our Shalop, to ſound a long the ſhoare, which about a muſket ſhot from the land, found ground at fortie fathom, ſmall blacke, and ſoft ſtonie grounde, ſometimes alſo they had twentie and thirty fathom, but as ſoone as they were a Shalops length or two from it, they had no ground againe. Then ten or twelue Canoes came to our ſhippe, but wee would not let them come aboord, but ſhewed them friendly countenance, and bartered with them for foure flying fiſhes, for the which wee gaue them ſome beades, which wee let downe by a rope at the ſterne of the ſhip, and they taking them tyed the fiſhes to the rope, and wee puld them vp, in the meane time our Shalop ſounded along by the land, which they in the Canoes ſeeing, preſently made towards it, and being cloſe by it, at firſt ſpake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the men, but withall compaſt them about with foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Canoes, and therewith ſome of them leapt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord, thinking to fall vpon the Shalop, or to draw it away with them, which our men perceiuing, ſhot with their Muskets among them, (there being ſix Muskets, and other armes. Courtelaſſes and Pikes in the Shalop) and therewith kild two of the <hi>Indians</hi> as they ſat in their Canoes, whereof one preſently fell dead ouerboorde, the other ſate ſtill with his hand vviping off the bloud vpon his breaſt, but at laſt fell likewiſe ouer boord:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17309:28"/>the reſt in the Canoes, were thereat in ſo great feare, that in all haſt they made away, at which time wee ſaw many men ſtanding vpon the ſhore, that cryed and made a great noyſe. But for that wee there could finde no fit anchoring ground, we tooke our Shalop in againe, and went forward on our voyage, holding our courſe ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt, the better to get to the ſouth, hoping there to find firme land. And it was ſo rough neere to the Iſland, that it was a very bad place for a boate to goe on ſhoare. The Iſland was all full of blacke cliffes, greene on the top, and blacke earth, and was full of Cocos trees, and greene herbes. Wee alſo ſaw many houles along by the Sea ſide, and clofe by the ſtrand there was a great Village, the land was hilly, but not very high.</p>
            <p>The fifteene wee were vnder ſixteene degrees twelue minutes, faire wether, the winde ſoutheaſt, our courſe weſt, and weſt and by ſouth.</p>
            <p>The 17. the winde being Northeaſt, wee went weſt and by ſouth, but the two laſt quarters, wee ſaylde weſt north weſt. That day it was agreed among vs, becauſe our victuales beegan to waxe ſcant, that in ſteede of breakfaſt, wee ſhould giue our men, halfe a cuppe of ſacke.</p>
            <p>The 18. being vnder 16. degrees, 5. minutes, wee had variable weſt windes, that day wee cald our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell together, to whom <hi>William Corneliſon Schouten</hi> our Maiſter ſhewed, that then wee were at the leaſt one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſixe hundred leagues, eaſtward from the coaſt of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru,</hi> and <hi>Chili,</hi> and had not diſcoured any part of <hi>Terra Auſtralis,</hi> as our intent was, that there was not any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance to diſcouer any thing to our contentments that wee alſo had ſayled further weſtward, then wee intended, that ſayling foreward in that maner, without all doubt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17309:29"/>wee ſhould fall ſouthward vpon <hi>Noua Guinea,</hi> and that if there wee ſhould finde no paſſage or way to gette through, (it being very dangerous, vncertaine and not knowne) that then both ſhippe and goods would be loſt, and wee our ſelues likewiſe ſhould periſh, it being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to come Eaſtward backe againe from thence, by reaſon of the ſteadfaſt Eaſt vvindes, that in the vveſt parts continually blow, that we alſo had but ſmall ſtore of victuals, and ſaw no meanes as yet to encreaſe them, and therefore asked their counſell, whether it was not their beſt way to alter their courſe, and to ſayle north<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard, thereby to get northvvard to <hi>Noua Guinea,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>Molucoes,</hi> which they conſidering of, and vvell weighing found his reaſons to be true, and thought it neceſſary to be done, and therefore all with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent agreed to ſayle Northward, not to fall ſouthward vpon <hi>Noua Guinea,</hi> being an vncertaine way, but rather Northward, to holde a certaine courſe, which was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently put in effect, and we ſet our courſe north northweſt</p>
            <p>The nineteenth, the winde South, and our courſe North, at noone vvee ſaw two Iſlandes, Northeaſt and by Eaſt, about eight leagues from vs, which ſeemed to lie about a Cannon ſhot diſtant one from the other. Then wee went northeaſt, to ſayle about the land, with faire weather, but no great gale.</p>
            <p>The 20. The wind was northeaſt, and we did the beſt by labouring to get to the land.</p>
            <p>The one and twentieth, the winde was Eaſt, with a ſmall gale: and when wee were about a league from the land, there came twentie Canoes to our ſhip, to whom wee ſhewed all ſignes of friendſhipp, but one of them with a wooden <hi>Aſſagay</hi> (ſharpe at the poynt) in his hand, threatened to ſhoote at one of our men, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17309:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>alowde, as they did in the other Iſland, vvhich vvee thought was a ſigne among them, to fall vpon vs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon we diſcharged two of our great Peeces, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall ſome of our Muskettes, whereby two of them were hurt, and the reſt preſently made away, as they fledde throwing a ſhirt overboord, which they hadde ſtolen out of our gallery. After that, ſome of them tooke courage againe, and came once more with certaine Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noes to our ſhippe, and wee ſayling cloſer to the land becauſe we had no ground, put out our Shalop to ſound the depth, with 8. musketiers in it, but they found no ground, and when they thought to come backe againe to the ſhip, 6. or 8. Canoes boorded them, thinking to enter the boate, and to take their armes from them: wherewith to defend themſelues they were forced to ſhoot with their muskets among them, and kild ſix, and hurt many of them, for when they fled our men rowed to one of their Canoes, that had no man in it but one that lay dead, whoſe leggs hung ſtill in the Canoe, they threw his body into the Sea, and brought the Canoe aboord their Shalop, wherein they found a Club, with a long ſtaffe like a halfe pike. In the night time our men came againe to vs and could find no anchor ground, and therefore that night we held off and on cloſe by the land.</p>
            <p>The 22. we did the beſt we could to get to the land, and comming to it, ſent out our Shalop to ſound along by the ſhore, that found ground at fiftie fathome, ſheluie ground about a Cannon ſhot from the land, which ſtill leſſened and waxt ſhallower to 30. and 35. fathome and vvee anchored at 35 fathome, ſheluie ground, till vvee could find a better place. Our ſhippe maſter rowed with the Shalop and our boate to ſound euery where, and found a fit place to lay the ſhippe in, which was cloſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17309:30"/>by our ſhippe, in a creeke, hard by a litle freſhe riuer, whereunto wee preſently ſayled, and for that the winde was contrarie, wee ſayled into it, ſo that being in the bay we lay a ſtones caſt off from the ſhoare, in the creeke at nine fathom water ſheluie ground. There we made our ſhip faſt with foure ropes, in ſmooth water, and the freſh water ranne downe out of the hill into the ſea, right againſt the place where our ſhippe lay, whereby while our men fetcht water, or did anything vpon the ſhoare, if the Indians hadde ſet vpon them, wee could beate them off with our ordinance. The ſame day there came diuers Canoes to our ſhippe, bringing ſome Cocos nuttes, and Vbas rootes, others brought a liue hog, and two roſted hogs, for the which wee bartered and gaue them ſlight kniues, beades, and nayles. Thoſe people al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo were theeuiſh, and would ſwim and diue exceeding well, as thoſe in the other Iſlands could doe, their houſes ſtood along the ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d which were round &amp; made of leaues ſharpe on the top and cloſe like a paint-houſe, to let the water fall downe, about fiue and twentie foote in compas, and ten or twelue foot high, with a low hole to goe in ſtooping, in them there was nothing to bee ſeene, but ſome dried herbes, like haye, to ſleepe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and an angling rodd or two, and in ſome a wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den club or ſtaffe, that was all their houſe-hold ſtuffe, both the beſt and worſer ſort, for the king himſelfe had no more.</p>
            <p>The 23 we bartered againe for more Cocos nuts, and Vbas rootes, which the Canoes brought to our ſhip, that day there came a great number of men downe to the ſtrand, which as it ſeemed came from all places of the Iſland, wondring to ſee our ſhip.</p>
            <p>The 24. <hi>Aris Clauſon, Reymie Simonſon Snocke,</hi> and <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neliſon
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17309:30"/>Schouten</hi> went on land to bee hoſtages, to make friendſhip with the Indians, and for them wee had 6. of their principall men in our ſhippe, whom wee vſed friendly, giuing them meate and drinke, and ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, as they did to our men, giuing them Cocos, and Vbas rootes to eate, and water to drinke. The king ſhewed our men great reuerence, and gaue them foure litle hogs, that day our men fetcht fiue fats full of water peaceably with out quarreling, for when any of the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans came neere our boate, the king himſelfe came the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and draue them thence, or ſent one of his men to doe it. His men were very obedient vnto him: for as it chanced that one of our coutelaſſes was ſtolen away from vs, and wee told one of the kings gentlemen thereof, hee gaue ſome of the Indians charge to fetch it againe, and preſently he that had taken it, was ſought for, and although hee was gone a good way of, they brought him backe who being come, the coutelaſſe was layd downe at our feete, &amp; he was beaten with ſtaues, they making ſignes vnto vs with their fingers vpon their throates, that if the <hi>Herico</hi> (that is the king) knew of it, his head ſhould be cut off, and after, that wee had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſtolen from vs, neither on the ſhoare, nor in the ſhippe, nor elſe where: neither durſt they take a fiſh that wee angled for. Thoſe people were very fearefull of our ſhooting, for when we ſhot off a muſket, they all ranne quaking and ſhivering away, and wee put them in more feare, when wee ſhewed them that vvee could ſhoot with the great peeces, which the king deſired vs once to doe, which being done they were all ſo fearefull and abaſht thereat, that all of them as alſo the king, (ſitting vnder his Belay, or canopy, notwithſtanding all that we could ſay or doe to perſwade them,) ſore ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17309:31"/>ranne into the woods, and left our men ſitting there alone. But not long after they came againe, ſcarſe halfe well aſſured.</p>
            <p>The 25. <hi>Aris Clawſon, Claus Iohnſon,</hi> and <hi>Daniel le Maire,</hi> went on land againe, to barter for hogs, but they would not barter. But after the king hadde ſayd his prayers, (which hee vſed to doe euery time that wee went on ſhore,) ſhewed vs great friendſhip, and we the like to him.</p>
            <p>The 26. <hi>Iacob le Maire</hi> our Marchant and <hi>Aris Claw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> went on ſhore but could get no hogs of the Indians, becauſe they themſelues hadde great neede of them, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing litle elſe to eate but Vbas rootes, Cocos nutts, a few hogs, and ſome Bananas, our men were very wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vnto them, and hadde great reuerence ſhewed them, for they trod vpon mats, and the king and his lieutenant gaue them their Crownes, which they tooke of from their owne heades, and ſet them on their heads, in recompence whereof, <hi>Iacob le Maire</hi> gaue them ſome preſents of litle worth, wherewith they were very well pleaſed.</p>
            <p>The crownes were made of long ſmall white feathers and vnderneath and aboue mixt with ſome red, &amp; greene feathers, for they haue many Parrots, and ſome Doues, whereof they make great account, for euery one of the kings counſell had a doue by him ſitting vpon a ſticke, thoſe Doues are white on their backes, and all the reſt blacke ſauing their breſts which are reddiſh, all that day wee fetcht water, and bartered for good ſtore of Cocos nuts, and Vbas rootes.</p>
            <p>The 27. and 28. wee got all our water into the ſhip, then <hi>William Corneliſon Schouten</hi> our maſter, and <hi>Aris Clawſon</hi> went on land with the trumpets, which the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17309:31"/>kings tooke great pleaſure to heare, and with much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe got two hogs.</p>
            <p>That day the king of the other Iſland came to viſit the king of the Iſland where wee were, who after great reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and wonderfull ceremonies vſed one vnto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, gaue each other certaine preſents, as roots and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, at laſt making a great noyſe, as we geſt, becauſe the king of the other Iſland deſired to try if he could take our ſhippe, and to keepe our men there, which the other king would not conſent vnto, fearing ſome hurt might happen vnto them. The kings Lieuetenant or his Sonne came once aboord our ſhip, whom we vſed in good ſort, and wondred much to ſee it: that euening our men daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with the <hi>Indians,</hi> wherat they much reioyced, marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that we were ſo familiar, &amp; behaued our ſelues ſo cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſly among them, we were there as free &amp; friendly as if we had beene at home in our owne houſes.</p>
            <p>The nine and twentieth, in the morning, <hi>Iacoble Maire, Aris Clawſon,</hi> with <hi>Claus Iohnſon, Ban,</hi> and one of our Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots went on ſhore, and being there, went into the land, and climed vp vpon a hill, to ſee what fruite grew there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to behold the cituation of the Iſland, and being vpon the hill, the old king and his brother came thither to beare them company: there they ſaw nothing but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, and ſome valleys that were all bare, by reaſon of the great ſtore of raine that had fallen, they alſo found ſome red colour, wherewith the women colour their heads and faces, and when they ſaw that our men were weary with going, they made ſignes vnto them to goe downe to the ſhippe againe, and ledde them by a good way, to a place where there was ſome Cocos trees, full of nuts, there they made our men ſit downe, and the kings Lieuetenant putting a ſtring about his feete, or
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17309:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>his hands, climed quickely vp a ſmooth high tree, and in a trice fetcht downe 10. Cocos nuts, which at one cruſh with a ſticke or a piece of wood, he ſo ſoone open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that our men wondred to ſee it, They told vs that they alwayes had warre with the men of the other Iſland, and ſhewed vs many holes and caues in the hill, and buſhes and groues in the way, from whence they iſſued out, and ſpoyld and killed each other: and would gladly haue had vs goe with our ſhippe, to the other Iſland to helpe them there, to fight againſt thoſe <hi>Indians</hi> with our Peeces, but it being no profit vnto vs, vvee refuſed it. About noone our men came aboord againe, bringing with them the young King and his brother, that dined with vs, and while he ſate at the table, we told them that within two dayes we would goe from thence, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the young Kinge was ſo glad, that for Ioy, hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently leapt from the table, and going into the Galle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, cryed out, and ſayde, that within two dayes wee would be gon. They were in great feare of vs, (although we ſhewed them all the friendſhip we could,) and doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that we would take their Country from them. Hee promiſed vs that if we would goe thence in 2. dayes, hee would giue vs 10. hogs, &amp; a great number of Cocos nuts, which they called <hi>Ali.</hi> When we had dined, the old king came aboord our ſhip, who after their manner was a ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeemely perſon, about 60. yeares of age, bringing with him 16. of his counſell: we receiued and welcomed him as well as we might. When hee entered into the ſhip, he fell downe vpon his face, and prayed, then we ledde him into the hold, and there againe he prayed, he wondred much at that hee ſaw, as wee alſo did at his behauiour: his men kiſt our feete, and tooke them in their handes, and laid them on their heads and their neckes, in ſigne
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17309:32"/>of ſubmiſſion. The King looked into all places of the ſhippe, both before and behinde, and lookt as if he had beene in a dreame, but ſpecially hee wondered at the great Ordinance, for 2. dayes before he had heard them ſhot off, to honour him. When he had ſeene the ſhip in euery place he deſired to goe on land againe, and vvent away with great reuerence made vnto vs. Our Marchant went with him, till he came to his <hi>Belay,</hi> where he ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily ſate, and then went out to walke with the young king, and about euening came aboord againe. In the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with moone-ſhine, <hi>Aris Clawſon</hi> went out to fiſh, and hauing taken a great ſhole of fiſh, went to the king, there he founde a number of young wenches dauncing before him, one played on a hollow piece of wood like a pump, which made a noyſe, whereat the young wenches daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced after their maner, very finely, and with a good grace, according to the meaſure of the noyſe of the Inſtrument. Our people wondred to ſee thoſe wilde people daunce in that ſort, and in the night they came on boord againe.</p>
            <p>The 30. In the morning, the king ſent vs 2. little hogs for a preſent: the ſame day, the King of the other Iſland came to ſee the King of that Iſland, &amp; with him brought 16. hogs, and 300. men in his company, all of them ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing certaine greene hearbs hanging about their midles, whereof they make their drinke. When the Kinge was neere vnto the other King, hee beganne a farre off with ſtrange ceremonies and reuerence to bow downe his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, falling with his face vpon the ground, &amp; praying with a great noiſe, and much zeale, as we thought. The other king went to meete him, and likewiſe with a great noyſe and ſtrange geſtures, vſed him very reuerently, and after much adoe, they both roſe vp on their feete, and went and ſate together vnder the kings <hi>Belay,</hi> and there were
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17309:33"/>aſſembled together at leaſt nine hundred men. When they went to ſit downe they prayed againe, according to their maner, hanging downe their heads, and bowing downe to the ground, holding their hands one in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which wee admired. After noone, <hi>Aris Clawſon</hi> being on ſhore, <hi>Iacoble Maire, Claus Iohnſon Ban,</hi> were ſent for, who went a ſhore, with foure trumpets and a drumme, to the two kings, there the trumpets blew, and the drum playd before them, wherein they tooke great pleaſure: after that came a company of Peſants, bringing with them a quantity of greene hearbs, which they called <hi>Caua,</hi> ſuch as the 300. men aforeſaide had about their midles, and all together at once began to chaw the herbs in their mouthes, which being chawd they tooke it out of their mouthes, and laid it all in a wooden veſſell, like a tray, or trough, and when they had chawd a great deale, they poured water into it, and ſo ſtirred and preſt it toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and gaue the liquor thereof to the kings to drinke, who dranke thereof with their gentlemen: they alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented that notable drinke (as a ſpeciall and a goodly preſent) to our men, but they had enough, and more then enough of the ſight thereof. They alſo brought a great number of Vbas rootes, which they had roſted, and ſixteene hogs that were onely ript, and the guts ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out, but all bloudy, and not waſht, and hauing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine hote ſtones put into their bellyes, and outwardly their haire ſinged off by the fire, were wel roſted after their maner, and they eate them as ſauourely and with as good an appetite, as wee could doe when they are well ſodden or roſted after our manner. Thoſe people yeeld great reuerence and reſpect vnto their Kinges, for all the meate vvhich they brought before their King, (who in their language they call <hi>Herico</hi>) they laid it vpon their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17309:33"/>heads, and kneeling on their knees, ſet it downe before the king. Of thoſe 16 hogs aforeſayd, each king gaue vs one, preſenting vs therewith in this ſort, firſt they layd them vpon their heads, and kneeling layd them with great humilitie at our feet, and with them gaue vs 11. litle liue hogs, and ſome indifferent great. And wee gaue them 3. copper beakers, 4. kniues, twelue old nailes, and ſome beades, where with they were well pleaſed. This feaſt, and meeting, our men ſaw with great delight &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, which done about euening they came aboord.</p>
            <p>The 31. in the morning, the kings of both Iſlands came aboord our ſhip, with their troupes of gentelmen, after their manner. The chiefe of them hadde greene Cocos leaues about their neckes, in ſigne of peace. We receiued them (as they had done to vs) with great reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and led them into the Cabbin, and into euery place of the ſhippe, and when they hadde ſeene all, they gaue vs ſix hogs. Both the kings themſelues layd them firſt one after the other vpon their heads, and then downe before our feet, with great humilitie, bowing their heads downe to the ground, meane time while wee tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the hogs, we led them into the cabbin againe, where wee gaue them two bundels of beades, and each king two kniues and ſix nayles, and there with they friendly tooke their leaue of vs, and went on land. <hi>Iacoble Maire</hi> our Marchant beare them company to the ſhore, to whom they gaue three hogs more. Which hee brought aboord the ſhippe, and then wee prepared our ſelues to ſet ſayle, to the great contentment of the Indians of that Iſland, becauſe as long as wee were there, they alwayes feared we would kil them, and take their country from them. Thoſe people were men of good vnderſtanding, and of great ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for the leaſt man of them was as big as the talleſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17309:34"/>of vs, and the talleſt of them was farre higher then any of vs, they were ſtrong men, and well proportioned of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and limbs, they went very faſt, and ſwam and diued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the water excellent well, their colour was altogether browne yealow, they were very curious in the dreſſing and trimming of their haire, ſome hadde it curled, ſome frizled, ſome ware it bound vp in long foldes 4.5. or 6. together, as our women doe in haire-laces, and ſome (which was ſtrange to ſee) had their haire ſtanding vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right vpon their heads, about a quarter of an elle long like hogs briſtles. The king had a long locke of haire on the left ſide of his head, that hung downe beneath his hipps, bound vp with a knot or two. His gentlemen hadde two ſuch lockes, on each ſide of their heads one, they went naked all alike both men and women, onely ſome litle thing handſomely tyed before their priuie mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. The women were very vnſightly both in face and body, of ſmall ſtature, Their haire cut cloſe to their heades, as our mens in <hi>Holland,</hi> their breſts long hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe to their bellies like lether ſatchels, they are very lecherous, for they ſuffer themſelues to be vſed by their men openly in all mens ſight, and in the kings owne preſence, onely vnder a mat. We could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that they worſhipped God, or any Gods, or vſed any deuotion, neither the one nor the other, but li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued without care, like birdes in the wood. They had no ſkill of buying or ſelling, but with flaggs they deliuered vs ſome what, and vvee in like ſort to them againe. They neither ſowe nor reape, nor doe any worke, There the earth of it ſelfe yeeldes all that they neede to ſuſtaine their liues: as Cocos, Vbas, Bananas, and ſuch like fruit. When the water falles. The women looke vpon the ſhoare on the ſea
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17309:34"/>ſide for fiſhes, and when they will, they take them with their hookes, and eate them raw, ſo that there men may plainely behold and ſee the golden world, whereof the Poets vvrite. When vvee left that Iſland, vvee called it <hi>Horne Iſland,</hi> after the name of the towne from whence vvee came, and the bay vvherein vvee anchored, the <hi>Vnities</hi> bay, after our ſhippes name: that day for the moſt part, vve were buſie to get out, and to hoyſe vp our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chors, one of our cables vvas fretted in peeces with the ſharpeneſſe of the ground where it lay, ſo vvee loſt that anchor, then wee drew vp an other anchor, and the cable fretting vpon a cliffe, brake as wee wound it vp and loſt that anchor alſo. This bay lies on the ſouth ſide of the <hi>Eye</hi> land, in a docke, on the one ſide their is a ſand, which at low water is dry, on the other ſide, the firme land but yet foule vpon the Shore. There vve lay with foure anchors and foure cables out, at 10. fathom ſandy ground, about a muſket ſhot from the litle riuer from vvhence the freſh water ran. Wee might vvell haue lyen with the ſhip in the litle riuer without danger, in the place vvhere vvee lay vve could not ſtirre, becauſe it vvas ſo narrovv: about noone vve vvere vnder ſayle, and ranne Weſt ſouth vveſt till euening, to get into the broad ſea, after that vve held our courſe vveſt, vvith an eaſt vvinde, glad that vve had eaſed and refreſhed our ſelues ſo vvell at that good Iſland, and vvere ſo vvell prouided of good vvater, ſome hogs, Vbas rootes, and a great number of Cocos nuts, and Bananas: the place vvhere vvee lay, is vnder 14. degees 56. minutes.</p>
            <p>The firſt of Iune, about noone we were vnder 13. degrees 15. minutes, the vvinde eaſt, our courſe North. The next day the vvind ſtill continued eaſterly, and vve went northvveſt and vveſt, and moſt part northvveſt and by
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17309:35"/>vveſt, with a hard courſe, vve vvere vnder 14. degrees 45. minutes, then wee ſavv great ſtore of birds, and held vveſt, and vveſt ſouth vveſt, with hollow billowes out of the ſouth ſoutheaſt.</p>
            <p>The 20. the winde northeaſt, wee vvent vveſt, and in the euening ſaw land, all that night driuing without ſayle, to keepe off from the land, and then were vnder 4. degrees 50. minutes.</p>
            <p>The 21. the winde eaſt, vvee made towards the land, that was very low and going neere vnto it, found many ſands which ſtrecht northvveſt of from the land, there were 3. or 4. Iſlands, all very ſmall but full of trees. There a Canoe boorded vs, being of the ſame faſhion as afore, but ſome what greater, able to hold 5 or 6 men. The men in all reſpectes as the former, and ſpake the ſame lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, but ſome what blacker hauing ſome thing before their priuie members. Their armes vvere bowes and arrowes, which were the firſt bowes that wee ſaw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Indians in the ſouth ſea, wee gaue them ſome beades and nayles, but they pointed towards the Weſt to tell vs that there was more land, where their king dwelt, and many things to be hadde. Therefore vve held our courſe vveſtvvard againe, finding no fit place to anchor in. This Iſland lay ſouth ſouthvveſt, and vveſt from vs, vnder 4. degrees 47. minutes.</p>
            <p>The 22. the winde eaſt ſouth eaſt, wee ſayld weſt, and vveſt and by north, vnder 4. degrees 45. minutes, that quarter wee hadde a good gale of vvinde, and faire wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that day ſaw at leaſt twelue or thirteene Iſlands, one cloſe by an other, vveſt ſouth vveſt from vs, reaching ſoutheaſt, and northvveſt about halfe a league, but ſayled along by them, leauing them on backeboord.</p>
            <p>The 24. the vvinde ſouth, at noone wee ſaw land on
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17309:35"/>back-boord, being 3. low Iſlands, that lay ſouthweſt from vs, very greene and full of trees, two of them were 2 miles long a peece, the third very litle, the ſhore was hard cliffie ground, there likewiſe we could find no anchoring: wee called them the <hi>Greene</hi> Iſlands. We alſo ſaw a high Iſland that had 7. or 8. houels forth right, lying weſt &amp; by north from vs, in the night we held off and on, ſtaying till day.</p>
            <p>The 25. in the morning, as wee were ſayling by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Iſland, we ſaw other land before vs, in the ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt, which was exceeding high, which we thought to be the poynt of <hi>Noua Guinea,</hi> we made towards it, leauing the other high Iſland that lay weſtward, which we called <hi>S. Iohns</hi> Iſland, becauſe it was <hi>S. Iohn Baptiſts</hi> day. About noone wee got to it, and ſayled along by it with an eaſt ſoutheaſt wind, but could find no anchor ground, we ſent out our Shalop to ſound the depth, that went along by the ſhore betweene the ſhip and it; and being ſomewhat neare the ſhore, there came 2. or 3. Canoes to it, with blacke <hi>Indians</hi> in them, all naked, without any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their members, which fiercely caſt ſtones at our men with ſlings, but as ſoone as our men began to ſhoote at them they fled away. The Shalop came on boord againe, without finding any ground, telling vs that the peoples language was cleane contrary to the former, we ſayled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long by the coaſt, which was very high and greene, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to behold, there we ſaw much land as it had bin hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, at euening we got about the point into a bay, there we anchored at 45. fathom, vnfit and vneuen ground. The ſame euening there came 2. Canoes to the ſhip, and ſpake to vs, but we vnderſtoode them not, all that night they held watch againſt vs, with fire all along their coaſt: we lay about a Cannon ſhot diſtant from the ſhore, againſt a run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning riuer: that night it was very ſtill calme moone-ſhine
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17309:36"/>weather, the wind on the land, there came ſome Canoes cloſe vnder the gallery of our ſhippe, from whence wee threw them ſome beades, ſhewing them all the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip wee could, withall making ſignes vnto them, to bring vs ſome Cocos nuts, hogs, oxen, or goates, if they had any, but they ſtayed ſtill moſt part of the night by vs, crying and hollowing after their manner. They were wilde blacke and rude men. This land as we geſt, lay di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from the coaſt of <hi>Peru,</hi> 1840. leagues.</p>
            <p>The 26. In the morning, there came 8. Canoes about our ſhip, whereof one had 11. men in it, the other 4.5.6. and 7. men. They rowed cloſe about our ſhippe, and were well furniſhed with armes after their manner, as <hi>Aſſagayes</hi> or Clubs, wooden ſwordes and ſlings, we ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them what friendſhip we could, and gaue them beades and other traſh, making ſignes to them to goe on ſhore, to ſetch vs hogs, hens, Cocos nuts, and other fruite, ſuch as they had, but they had another meaning, and all together began fiercely to ſling with their ſlings, &amp; other weapons, thinking to maſter vs, but we ſtanding vpon our guarde, ſhot with our muskets and great ſhot amongſt them, and ſlew at leaſt 10. or 12. of them: They left the great Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noe, and 3. other, and leaping into the ſea, ſwam to land, we put out our Shalop, and rowed with it among thoſe that ſwam away, and ſlaying ſome of them, brought three of them priſoners into our ſhippe, that were ſore wounded, and 4. of their Canoes, which we hewed in peeces, to make fire for the Cooke. The hurt men were cured, but one of them dyed, about noone our men row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the 2. wounded men to the land, along the ſhore, there the priſoners cryed to their fellowes to bring vs hogs, Bananas and Cocos nuts, wherewith one Canoe came aboord, that brought a little hog, and a bunch of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17309:36"/>Bananas, wee ſet one of the men at ten hogs ranſome, the other that was ſore hurt, we let goe in the Canoe, becauſe we doubted he would not liue, thoſe men had 2. holes bored in their noſes, on either ſide one, wherein they ware rings, ſtrange to beholde. There we ſaw an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iſland, lying North from that great Iſland.</p>
            <p>The 27. VVe fild our empty veſſels full of water, and that day we got a hog from the land, and there ſaw di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers red birds.</p>
            <p>The 28. there came certaine Canoes aboord our ſhip, but brought nothing with them, neither would they ranſom their man, therefore we let him goe on ſhore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Wee thought thoſe people to be <hi>Papoos,</hi> for all their haire was ſhort, and they eate Betell and Chalke mingled with it, that night wee hoyſed anchor, and ſet ſayle, with a ſmall gale of winde.</p>
            <p>The 29. the wind was variable, and our courſe was northweſt, and northweſt and by north, with faire wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther till noone, then it calmd. At euening we were ſtill in the ſight of the poynt of the Iſland, and yet we ſayled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long by the land, which reached northweſt, and north and by weſt, with many bayes and crookes. The ſame day vve ſavv three high Iſlands more, that lay northward from the great Iſland, about 5. or 6. miles. Then wee were vnder 3. degrees 20. minutes.</p>
            <p>The 30. in the morning, driuing in a calme, diuers Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noes with blacke <hi>Indians</hi> came aboord our ſhip, who in ſigne of peace, as they entred, brake their <hi>Aſſagayes</hi> ouer their heads, they brought vs nothing, but deſired ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of vs. They ſeemed to be better and friendlyer peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple then the other for they couered their priuie members with leaues, and had better kind of Canoes, ſet out before and behinde with ſome carued workes, they are
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17309:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>very proud of their beades, which they paint with chalke and the haire of their heads alſo. Vpon the three or foure Iſlands, from whence thoſe Canoes came, there was great ſtore of Cocos trees: they brought vs nothing, how earneſtly ſoeuer wee vrged them, that wee had neede of victuales: There they ſtayed till euening, and then went on land againe.</p>
            <p>The firſt of Iuly in the morning, after wee had dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen all the night in a calme, before the ſtreame about two leagues, wee anchored betweene an Iſland of two miles long, and the firme land of <hi>Guinea,</hi> about noone there came 25. Canoes toward our ſhip, with many men, well armed: being the ſame people who the day before brake their <hi>Aſſagaies</hi> ouer their heads, and made a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew vnto vs, but with intent to abuſe vs, as after it appeared, who ſeeing vs to lie in a calme, thought to take our ſhip from vs, we had 2. anchors hanging out before at the bough, a litle puld vp, whereon they ſate, on each anchor a man, with a <hi>Pingay</hi> or girdle in their hands, wherewith they vſe to hold or draw forth their Canoes, and ſo thought to draw the ſhip to ſhore, the reſt hung faſt vpon the ſhip, we ſtill ſtanding vpon our guarde: at laſt, they began fiercely to throw at vs with ſtones, and other weapons, and thereby hurt one of our men, being the firſt that was hurt in all our voyage, but while they were buſie to aſſaile vs, thinking they had got the vpper hand, we ſhot among them with our Muskets, and with our vpper tyre of Ordinance, and kild at leaſt 12. or 13. of them, and hurt many more: and while they fledde away, our men rowd with the ſhalop, (well armed) after them, and tooke one of their Canoes with 3. men in it, whereof one that was dead they threw ouer-boord, the other 2. leapt into the water, but one of them being kild by one of our
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17309:37"/>men, the other yeelded himſelfe priſoner, being a yong man about 18. yeares old, whom wee named <hi>Moſes,</hi> after our mans name that was hurt. Thoſe people eate bread made of rootes of trees. After this fight we ſaild all along by the land, with a good gale, weſt northweſt, and northweſt and by weſt.</p>
            <p>The 2. we were vnder 3. degrees 12. minutes, and that day ſaw low land on backe-boord, and alſo a great high hill, and right before vs a low Iſland, we ſayled ſoftly weſt northweſt, with ſlight water eaſt northeaſt.</p>
            <p>The third vvee ſaw high land againe, weſt from vs, about 14, leagues from the other Iſland, vnder 2. degrees and 40. minutes.</p>
            <p>The 4. as vve vvere buſied to paſſe by the aforeſayd 4. Iſlands, vvee ſaw at leaſt 22 or 23. others, great and ſmall, high and low, which wee left on ſtarrboord, onely two or three on larboord.</p>
            <p>They lay cloſe one by the other, ſome a league, or a league and a halfe, and ſome more then a Cannon ſhot, diſtant one from an other, vnder 2. degrees 25. or 30. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes litle more or leſſe. That euening wee hoped to finde a road, but were forced to holde becauſe night came on. The ſame time vvee ſavv a ſayle come toward vs from one of thoſe Iſlands but becauſe it was night, it boorded vs not, and in the morning the wind falling contrarie, we left it, and yet were cloſe by it.</p>
            <p>The 5. the winde being ſouth eaſt, and eaſt ſoutheaſt, and our courſe ſouth and by weſt, and ſouth weſt, vvee hadde much thunder and raine, and were vnder 3. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 56. minutes.</p>
            <p>The 6. ſometimes wee had a hard vvinde, and ſome times calme with raine, lightening and thunder, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noone ſaw a verie high hill being ſouthweſt from vs
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17309:38"/>which we ſayled vnto, our maſter was of opinion that it was <hi>Banda,</hi> by reaſon it was very like to the hill called <hi>Geomenapi</hi> in <hi>Banda,</hi> and very like for height, but going neere vnto it, wee might ſee two or three hills more like vnto it, that lay on the north ſide of the firſt hill, about 6. or 7. leagues diſtant, whereby we knew that it was not ſo. Behind that hill, wee ſaw very much land eaſt and weſtward, which vvas ſo long, that on either ſide wee could ſee no ende thereof, ſometimes high, and then low, reaching eaſt ſouth eaſt, whereby vvee geſt it to be <hi>Noua Guinea,</hi> and for that night came vpon vs we held off from it. The 7. in the morning, before day we wound againe towards the high hills, which was a burning Iſland, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fire and flame from the top thereof, and therefore we called it <hi>Vulcans Iſland,</hi> the winde then was ſouth weſt with faire weather. This Iſland was vvell inhabited, and had many Cocos trees in it, the people came with ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noes to our ſhip, but were very fearefull of vs, they called vnto vs, but we vnderſtood them not, neither could our blacke <hi>Moſes</hi> tell what they ſayd, they were all naked, onely their priuie members couered, their haire ſome ſhort, ſome long. There we found no ground, and ſo could not anchor. In the north and northvveſt, wee ſavv more Iſlands, at which time, wee went north vveſt and by vveſt to a low Iſland, that vve ſavv before vs, which in the euening we got vnto: Then we tooke in our ſayles, and let the ſhip driue. There we found diuers colours of water, greene, white, and yealow, which we geſt to be water com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of riuers, for it was ſweeter then the ſea wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. There many trees, leaues, and boughs draue in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whereon ſome birds and crabs ſat.</p>
            <p>The 8. the winde being variable, wee held our courſe weſt ſouth weſt, and vveſt north vveſt, vvith faire wether
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17309:38"/>and a reaſonable gale of winde, hauing on ſtarre-boord a high, and on larboord a low Iſland, reaſonable high, vve made toward the land, which about euening vve got vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and found good ſandie ground, at 70. fathom deepe, about a cannon ſhot from the land. There certaine Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noes came to vs, with a kind of ill fauoured people, all <hi>Papoos,</hi> their haire ſhort, and curled, hauing rings in their noſes and eares, and ſtrings about their heads or armes, and hogs teeth hanging about their neckes, for an orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. They alſo eate Betel, and were all defectiue perſons ſome great legs, others ſwolne armes, and ſo forth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is to be thought, that there about it is vnwholeſome land, &amp; the rather, becauſe their houſes ſtood vpon ſtakes, about 8 or 9. foote from the ground, there vvee had 3. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 43 minutes and found a litle ſhew of ginger.</p>
            <p>The 9. in the morning, lying at anchor, our Shalop rowed to looke for a fit place to anchor the ſhip in, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning told vs, that they had found a fit bay, where vnto we went, and anchored at 26 fathom good. ſandy ground mixt with clay. There about ſtood two ſmall villages, from whence there came many Canoes aboord our ſhip, that brought a fevv Cocos nuts, but they eſteemed them very deare, for 4. nuts asking a fathom of linnen cloth. Whereof they were very deſirous, they alſo hadde ſome hogs vvhich they held at a deerer rate, and what neede ſoeuer vve ſayd vvee hadde thereof and made ſignes to to them to bring vs ſome, they would not doe it. That day euery man in our ſhip had allowance of 5 pound of bread and a meaſure and a halfe of oyle a weeke, a cup and a halfe of Sacke a day, and a Niperkin of aquauita all our pottage, as peaſe, beanes, gurt: and our fleſh, bacon, and fiſh being ſpent, and vve knew not where vve vvere, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vncertaine whether vve were far or neere to the <hi>Indian
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17309:39"/>Iſlands,</hi> as alſo what place vve vvere in, though vve ſayled continually by the land, not knowing vvhether it was <hi>Noua Guinea</hi> or no, vve onely geſt at it, for all the Cardes that vvee had, did not agree, nor were not like to the land that vve ſaw. That euening vve had great ſtore of raine, vvith thunder and lightening, which held all night with very darke weather.</p>
            <p>The 10. there came at leaſt 20. Canoes, on boord of our ſhip, with men, women, and children in them, all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, only their priuie members couered, but brought no great matter with them.</p>
            <p>The 11. in the morning vve put to ſea againe, and held our courſe north vveſt, and by weſt, and weſt north weſt along the coaſt, with the land alwayes in ſight 3.2. and a league and a halfe diſtant from it, and at noone paſt by a high point. That land of <hi>Noua Guinea</hi> for the moſt part reacheth north weſt and by weſt, ſometimes ſome what more vveſterly, and ſometimes againe more norther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The 12. we ſailed ſtil weſt northweſt, along by the coaſt with faire wether, and without ſun ſhine, at noone being vnder 2. degrees 58. minutes, with help of the ſtreame, that ſet vs about the weſt, as it did all along the coaſt of <hi>Noua Guinea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 13. and 14. Wee ſayled along by the aforeſay de coaſt, ſometime by high and then by low land.</p>
            <p>The 15. We had the winde, and held our courſe as afore ſayd, along by the coaſt, with good wether, after-noone we came to 2. low inhabited Iſlands, about halfe a league from the maine land, which ſtood full of Cocos trees. We made towards them, and there found good anchor ground, at 40.30.25. and 20. to 6. and 5. fathom deepe, and there anchored at 13. fathom good ground. The maſter rowed with the boate and the Shalop well armed,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17309:39"/>to the land, thinking to get ſome Cocos nuts, which there vvere vpon the land in great aboundance: but going on ſhore, the <hi>Indians</hi> lay in a buſh right againſt the place where wee came to land, and watching for vs, ſhot ſo fiercely at vs with their bovves, that they hurt at leaſt 16. of our men, ſome in the arme, others in the leg, necke and hands, and other places. And we ſhot at them with muskets and ſlings, but at laſt by reaſon that the <hi>Indians</hi> ſhot ſo thicke we vvere forced to retire, there vve vvere vnder. 2 degrees 54. minutes.</p>
            <p>The 16. in the morning vvee ſayled in with our ſhippe between both the Iſlands, and anchored at 9 fathome, where vve had good lying, after noone our boate and Shalop rowed to the leſſer Iſland, to fetch ſome Cocos, and burnt 2 or 3. of the Indians houſes, whereupon they that dwelt in the other Iſland began mightily to crie and make a noyſe, but durſt not come to vs, for with our ordinance we ſhot along the ſhore, and into the wood, that the bullets entered into it with thundring noyſe, whereat the Indians fled, and durſt not once looke out, about euening our men came aboord againe, and brought ſo many Cocos nurs, that euery one of vs had three nuts for his part. That night there came one of the Indians aboord our ſhippe to make peace with vs, with him bringing one of our mens caps with before fell off his head in the skirmiſh. Thoſe people are cleane naked, their priuie members and all.</p>
            <p>The 17. in the morning, there came 2 or 3 Canoes towards our ſhip, and threw Cocos nuttes into the water making ſignes to vs to fetch them, whereby they ſought to be friends with vs, Wee made ſignes to them to come aboord, at laſt taking better courage, they came cloſe to the ſhippe, and brought vs as many Cocos nuttes and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:17309:40"/>Bananas as we deſired, which wee drew vp by ropes into the gallery, giuing them old nayles, ruſtie kniues, and beades in barter, they alſo brought vs a litle greene gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and yealow rootes which are vſed in ſteed of Saffron, bartered alſo with vs ſome of their bowes and arrowes, ſo that at laſt we were great friends with them.</p>
            <p>The 18. we bartered ſtill for Cocos nuttes and Bananas and ſome Caſſauie and Papede, which is alſo to be had in eaſt <hi>India.</hi> There we ſaw ſome <hi>Potteyſen</hi> which as wee thought came from the <hi>Spaniardes.</hi> Thoſe people were not ſo inquiſitiue to looke into our ſhip, as others were, for they knew what ſhooting with great peeces ment, and cald the Iſland wherein they dwelt, <hi>Moa,</hi> which lay moſt eaſterly, the other ouer againſt it they called <hi>Iuſou,</hi> and the vtter moſt (being a very high Iſland) lying about 5 or 6. leagues from <hi>Noua Guinia,</hi> they named, <hi>Arimoa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 19. our men went to the greateſt Iſland to fiſh, There the <hi>Indians</hi> ſhewed vs great friendſhip, and holpe our men to draw vp their nets, and gaue them as many Cocos nuttes as they deſired, There wee ſaw a great number of Canoes comming towards vs out of the eaſt, from other Iſlands lying caſtward, whereof ſome were indifferent great, Therefore wee called our fiſhermen on boord, The <hi>Indians</hi> that were by vs, made ſignes to vs to ſhoot at thoſe Canoes, and our men made ſignes againe that they would, if they ſhot firſt at vs, but they came peaceably aboord, and brought vs as many Cocos nuttes and Bananas as we deſired, ſo that euery man had 50. nuttes and two bunches of Bananas. Thoſe people vſe Caſſauie for their bread, but it is nothing like to that of the vveſt <hi>Indies,</hi> they bake it alſo in round cakes.</p>
            <p>The 20. In the morning wee ſet ſayle, after wee had againe bartered for more victualls, they made ſignes to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17309:40"/>vs to lie ſtill, and they would bring vs more.</p>
            <p>The 21. we ſayled along by the land Weſt northweſt, and at noone were vnder 1 degree 13. minutes. Then wee ſavv a number of Iſlandes, whereunto the ſtreame draue vs, and about noone wee got to them, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chored at 13. fathom. That euening we had much raine, thunder, and lightening.</p>
            <p>The 23. in the morning we ſet ſayle, with good vvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and a good gale, and being a litle from the land, 6. great Canoes follovved vs, (and yet, vve ſavv no men on land) bringing dried fiſh, (which vvee tooke to be Steen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braſſes,) Cocos nuts, Bananas, Tabacco, and ſome ſmall fruits like Prunes. There alſo came ſome <hi>Indians</hi> from on other Iſland that brought vs ſome victualles, that alſo had ſome Chinay porceline, for we bartred for two diſhes whereby we were perſwaded that many Chriſtian ſhippes had bin there, for they wondered not, as others did, at our ſhip. They were another kind of people then the former, of a yealower colour, and greater of body, ſome of them hadde long haire, ſome ſhort, and alſo vſed bowes and arrowes, whereof wee had ſome in barter. They were very deſirous of beades, and iron worke, and had greene blew, and white glas rings, ſticking in their eares: which we geſt they had from the <hi>Spaniardes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 24 we were vnder halfe a degree, with a litle gale, and ſayled north weſt, vveſt and ſouth weſt, along by a faire great Iſland, very greene and pleaſant to behold, which wee called <hi>William Schoutens Iſland,</hi> after our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters name, and the vveſt point thereof, the cape of good <hi>Hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 25. we ſaw much land on larboord lying ſouth ſouthweſt from vs, ſome very high, and ſome very low.</p>
            <p>The 27. wee ſaw three Iſlands more, the coaſt reacht,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:17309:41"/>Northweſt and by weſt.</p>
            <p>The 27. we were vnder 29. minutes ſouthward of the line, and ſaw much land ſouthward from vs, ſome high, and ſome very low, and paſt vveſt north weſt along by it.</p>
            <p>The 28. and 29. the wether was variable, that night we hadde an earthquake, which made our men for feare to run out of their cabbins, our ſhippe ſeeming as if it ſtroke againſt the ground, but wee caſt out our leade, and found no ground.</p>
            <p>The 30. vve ſayled in a great bay or hollow place, ſo that wee ſeemed to be round about in cloſed with the land, we did our beſt to finde an opening, but could not, and therefore ſayled northward againe, that day it thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and lightened ſo ſore, that our ſhippe ſhooke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and ſometime ſeemed to be on a light fire, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wee were in no ſmall feare, and after it, enſued ſo great a ſhower of raine that wee neuer had ſeene the like before.</p>
            <p>The 31 we perceiued that we were entred into a place where we had the land round about vs, therefore we held our courſe north, and that euening paſt the Equinoctiall line the ſecond time, and being cloſed by the land, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chored at 12. fathom good ground, about a Cannon ſhot from an Iſland, that lay cloſe by the firme land, but there wee ſaw no men nor any thing growing.</p>
            <p>The firſt of Auguſt, wee hoyſed anchor with great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, for it lay vnder a cliffe, but at laſt we got it vp, we were then 15. minutes northward of the line, in the euening with the hard ſtreame, we went cloſe to the land and by reaſon it was calme, anchored in vneuen ground, and not deepe.</p>
            <p>The 2. it was very calme and we draue with the ſtreame weſt and weſt and by north, with rainie weather.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:17309:41"/>
            <p>The 3. vve held our courſe as before, with a calme, and found a bancke, ſo farre in the ſea that wee could ſcarſe ſee the land, in ſome places being 40. in an other 20.15. and 12. fathom ſandy ground, wee anchored at 12. fathom, becauſe it waxt night, and the maſter deſired to ſee how the ſtreame went, it was weſt ſouthweſt. The ſame day we were vnder 35. minutes northward of the line, and ſavv many Whales, and Tortices. Wee geſt by the height that wee were at the ende of the land of <hi>Noua Guinea,</hi> hauing ſailed along by the coaſt 280. leagues that day wee ſaw 2 Iſlands more weſtward from vs.</p>
            <p>The 4. the winde variable, our courſe was ſouth weſt, then it rained much with cloudy weather, there the ſtreame went hard weſt, that day we ſavv 7. or 8. Iſlands as we thought, and there in the night lay aloofe, to keepe off from the land.</p>
            <p>The fiſt in the morning, wee draue in a calme, with a variable winde, our courſe ſouth and ſouth eaſt, with rainie weather and a little gale, but the winde being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, wee made towards the land, which the day before wee tooke to be Iſlands, but comming to them found no ground, and therefore put out our Shalop to ſound, and found ground at 45. fathom, cloſe by the land. As our Shalop rowed to land, wee ſaw firſt 2. and then 3. Canoes more come of from the land, and made towards our Shalop, and being hard by it, put out a flag of peace, and our men the like, and then went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord, the Canoes followed them and alſo came aboord, they brought vs nothing but a muſter or ſhew of Indian Bonties, and Erties, with ſome Ryce, Tabacco, and two Paradice brids: wee bartered for one of them that was white and yeallow. We could vnderſtand them reaſonable well, for they ſpake <hi>Tarnata</hi> words, and one of them ſpake
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17309:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>good <hi>Malaian,</hi> which language <hi>Aris Clawſon</hi> our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant could ſpeake well, ſome of them ſpake ſome <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh,</hi> and among them they had a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> felt. They wore faire clothes, about their middles, and ſome hadde ſilke breeches on of diuers colours, ſome alſo had wreaths about their heads, which they ſay, were <hi>Turkes</hi> or <hi>Moores.</hi> They ware gold and ſiluer rings vpon their fingers, their haire was all coale blacke. They bartred their ware with vs for beades, but rather deſired Linnen: They were very warie and fearefull of vs. VVe askt them what the name of this countrie was, but they would not tell vs, but by many circumſtances wee Iudged, and verely beleeued, that we were at the eaſt ende of <hi>Gilolo,</hi> on the midlemoſt point of the land, (for <hi>Gilolo</hi> reacheth out with 3. pointes to the eaſt) and that they were men of <hi>Tidore,</hi> friends to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> as we alſo found it ſo to be, which made vs all reioyce that after ſo many windings and turnings, and troubles endured, we were come to the place which wee knew, and hoped in ſhort time to come among our country men, a thing which vve ſo long, and ſo much had hopt for and deſired. Then wee had a ſmall gale of winde, and anchored vnder the land, a Cannon ſhot from the ſhoare, at 40. fathom, where they brought vs Cocos and other fruit to buy, they told vs that vvee lay not vvell there, and it was true, for in the euening vvee had a good gale and draue through. That night the Canoes vvent avvay from vs, promiſing the next day to bring vs home, that day wee were the third time right vnder the Equinoctiall line.</p>
            <p>The 6. in the morning, they came againe from the land, aboord our ſhippe, and brought ſome Tabacco, and porceline and ſome other things: but vve hauing a good gale, ſouth ſouth eaſt, and bad lying there, hoyſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anchor
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:17309:42"/>to goe on our voyage to the <hi>Moluccos,</hi> and held our courſe north, with a good gale to goe north, about the north point of <hi>Gilolo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 7. it rained, and we ſavv the north eaſt point of <hi>Gilolo,</hi> called <hi>Moratay,</hi> vvhich lay ſouth eaſt from vs.</p>
            <p>The 8. about noone vvee vvere vnder 4. degrees 3, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes northvvard of the line, that night it rained hard vvith thunder and lightening, there vve found the ſtream to goe northward.</p>
            <p>The 9. and 10. the vvinde vvas variable, vvith rainie vveather, and vvere vnder the heigh of 3. degrees 50. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes.</p>
            <p>The 11. in the morning, wee ſawe the land of <hi>Gilolo</hi> called <hi>Moratay,</hi> againe on the northeaſt point of <hi>Gilolo,</hi> wee did the beſt wee could to reach it, but the ſtreame put vs of from the land towardes the north, and coulde not reach it that day.</p>
            <p>The 12. and 13. we were vnder 2. degrees 58. minutes, with variable windes, and much raine, and the like, the 14.15. and 16.</p>
            <p>The 17. with great labour and much trouble wee got vnder the land, late in the euening, and draue along by the coaſt with faire wether, that night we ſaw many fires vpon the land.</p>
            <p>The 18. it was ſtill wether, and we draue along by the land, about noone two Canoes came to vs with a flag of peace, from the Village called <hi>Soppy,</hi> they were <hi>Tarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taens,</hi> with whom wee could ſpeake well, and ſome of them were of <hi>Gammacanor,</hi> they ſhewed vs that a Pinnace of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had laine there three months to lade Ryce, and that about a moneth or two before, alſo an Engliſh ſhip had beene there. How glad we were then when we were ſo well aſſured, that wee were come to ſo good and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17309:43"/>long deſired a place, after ſo much paine and trouble that we had endured, with 85. ſound men, vvhen vvee had ſpent all our victuals, euery man may iudge that hath proued the like aduenture. There vve vvere vnder tvvo degrees, 47. minutes, and anchored at 28. fathom, ſome of thoſe men ſtayed that night vvith vs, the next day to bring vs to the road of <hi>Soppy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 19. vvee ſayled into the bay, and there anchored at 10. fat hom ſandy ground, about a Cannon ſhot from the ſhore. That day we bartered for ſome Sagovv, ſome Hennes, 2. or 3. Tortoyſes, and a little Rice.</p>
            <p>The 20. wee bartered for a great deale of Sagow and ſome Ryce, for Linnen, Beades, Kniues, Glaſſes, and Combes. While wee were there, a <hi>Correcor</hi> came thether to prouide Ryce and Sagow for the King of <hi>Tarnata,</hi> who told vs, that there was at leaſt 20. ſhips, Hollanders and Engliſhmen round about the Iſland of <hi>Tarnata</hi> that lay there: and that there was 8. ſhips at the <hi>Manillas,</hi> whereof foure were Engliſh and foure Dutch: There we got good ſtore of fiſh.</p>
            <p>The 21.22.23. and 24. we ſtill bartered for Sagow and Ryce, by the ſmall meaſure.</p>
            <p>The 23. our men made an end of their wine.</p>
            <p>The 25. in the euening, we ſet ſayle, after we had laden 4. Tunne of Rice, and good ſtore of Sagovv.</p>
            <p>The next day to the 5. of September, we ſtill had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and variable vvindes, vvith calmes, and ſometimes great billovves, and much raine, ſo that with great labour and trouble vvee ſailed along that coaſt, oftentimes tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and winding to and fro, anchoring diuers times in a day, and ſetting ſayle againe, but the great hope that we had, ſoone to get to <hi>Tarnata</hi> to our Countrymen, made all our labour light and eaſie.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:17309:43"/>
            <p>The 5. vvhile vvee lay before the coaſt of <hi>Gilolo</hi> at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, our men vvent out to fiſhe, and vvhile they vvere dravving vp their net, there came 4. <hi>Tarnatans</hi> leaping out of the vvood, each of them vvith a ſvvord and target in their hands, thinking to kill our men, but the Surgion crying out <hi>Oran Hollanda,</hi> they preſently forbare to aſſaile them, throvving vvater vpon their heads and ſaid, that they thought our men had beene <hi>Spaniards,</hi> our men brought them aboord our ſhippe, and gaue them ſome beades, for the vvhich they promiſed to bring vs that we needed. They told vs that they came from <hi>Gammaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> from whence by their ſaying, we were as then at leaſt 5. or 6. leagues diſtant.</p>
            <p>The 6. and 7. we ſtill had calmes, and contrary winds, often hoyſing our anchors, and ſetting ſaile many times, winding and turning to further our voyage, but to no effect, ſo that wee were forced to attend the time, with litle furtherance.</p>
            <p>The 8. wee ſtill lay at anchor, with contrary windes, meane time our chiefe Marchant and the Marchant of the <hi>Horne,</hi> with the Shalop well armed, went to <hi>Gamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canor,</hi> thinking there to get ſome refreſhing. The coaſt from <hi>Soppy</hi> to <hi>Gammacanor</hi> reacheth ſouthweſt and north<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt, with many bayes and creekes. There the ſtreame ran northward.</p>
            <p>The 9. and 10. Wee ſtill lay at anchor with contrary wind, as alſo the 11. then our Shalop came againe, and had not beene at <hi>Gammacanor,</hi> becauſe it was too farre diſtant from vs, and they were vnprouided of victuals, but had beene in a village called <hi>Lolola,</hi> about 10. leagues diſtant from the place where our ſhip lay, where they one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly got ſome Bananas, which were there to be hadde in great abundance. The inhabitants told them that the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:17309:44"/>
               <hi>Dutchmen</hi> and the <hi>Tarnatans</hi> had taken an Iſland, called <hi>Sianno,</hi> lying vpon the paſſage of the <hi>Manillas,</hi> and that there lay 13. ſhips in <hi>Tarnata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 12. our Maſter and <hi>Aris Clawſon</hi> with 18. men well armed went to <hi>Tarnata,</hi> from whence (as we geſt) we were diſtant at leaſt 25. Leagues, and we lay ſtill at anchor with our ſhip in a calme.</p>
            <p>The 13. the calme ſtil held, and our men going out to fiſh, there came 3. Peſants or country people out of the land to them, and brought them 3. hogs, indifferent great, which they ſayd they had taken with dogs, for the which we payd them to their contentment.</p>
            <p>The 14 about noone, wee ſet ſayle with an indifferent gale, but yet twas calme, ſo that in the ſame quarter we got but 2. leagues and a halfe forward, and that with great labour.</p>
            <p>The 15. it blew a litle gale, and in that quarter we got about 4 Leagues further, with faire weather.</p>
            <p>The 16. wee paſt by <hi>Gammacanor,</hi> and ſaw <hi>Tarnata</hi> and <hi>Tidore,</hi> lying cloſe one by the other vpon 2. high hilles, ſouth from vs, about 12. leagues diſtant.</p>
            <p>The 17. we had a good gale, and did our beſt to get to <hi>Tarnata,</hi> that morning betimes we ſavv a ſayle to loofe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from vs, which alſo made towards <hi>Tarnata,</hi> being the <hi>Morning Sarre</hi> of <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> of 300. Tunnes burthen, hauing in her 26. great pieces. At noone our Shalop came from that ſhip, where ſhe had lyen 3. nights, they being in the Creeke of <hi>Sabou,</hi> found there the Adminall <hi>Verhaghen</hi> there, in one of the Admirall <hi>Speilberg</hi> his ſhips, by whoſe men we vnderſtood, that <hi>Speilberg</hi> being in the Straights of <hi>Magelan,</hi> (which he paſt in 2. Monthes) had loſt his ſmalleſt Pinnace, and that in the riuer of <hi>Spirito Santo,</hi> on the coaſt of <hi>Braſilia,</hi> hee had loſt 3. boates with
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:17309:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>men in them, that he had ſpoyled the towne of <hi>Payta,</hi> and had fought with 8. <hi>Spaniſh ſhippes,</hi> whereof he had ſuncke three, viz. the Admirall, the vice Admirall, and an other, without any great hurt, onely the loſſe of ſome men, and got nothing. That he had bin at <hi>Lima,</hi> and ſearched many creekes, where the <hi>Spaniſh ſhips</hi> lay vp: and in one, wherein there was 40. ſhippes, but did nothing, and that he ſayld along by the coaſt of <hi>Noua Spania,</hi> through the <hi>Manillas</hi> to the eaſt <hi>Indies</hi> being from thence gone home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with <hi>Iohn Corneliſon Meuſcheater</hi> with 4. ſhips: their names, the <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> the armes of <hi>Amſterdam, Zeland,</hi> and <hi>Midleburgh.</hi> They alſo told vs, that there were 10. ſhips well furniſhed at the <hi>Manillas,</hi> their generall being <hi>Iohn Dirickeſon Lam</hi> of <hi>Horne,</hi> to ſet vpon the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> fleete, that were comming to <hi>Tarnata.</hi> We alſo vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that <hi>Peter Bot</hi> ſayling home with 4. Ships, was caſt away, vpon <hi>Mauricius</hi> Iſland, with 3. ſhips, by meanes of a ſtorme that caſt him vpon the cliffes, where many of his men and himſelfe alſo was drowned, the 4. ſhip ſcapt.</p>
            <p>The ſame euening we anchored before <hi>Maleye in Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata,</hi> at 11. fathome ſandy ground, with great Ioy that we were come among our Countrymen: our Maſter and the Marchant went preſently on ſhore, to ſpeake with the Generall <hi>Laurence Real,</hi> who was come thither in the place of the deceaſed Generall <hi>Gerard Reynſts,</hi> where they were well entertained by him, as alſo by the Admirall <hi>Stephen Verhaghen,</hi> and <hi>Iaſper Ianſon</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bona</hi> as likewiſe of the whole Counſell of <hi>India.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 18. our Maſter and the Marchants went on land, and ſold our two Shalops, foure great peeces of the <hi>Horne,</hi> ſome Lead, two great Cables, nine anchors and other things, for the which they receiued a thouſand three hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred and fifty Ryals of eight.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:17309:45"/>
            <p>The 19.20.21.22. and 23. we lay at anchor in the ſame place.</p>
            <p>The 24. eleuen of our men and foure boyes prayed our Maſter <hi>William Corneliſon Schouten</hi> to diſcharge them, deſiring to ſtay a while there in <hi>India,</hi> to ſerue the Eaſt <hi>Indian</hi> Company, which our Maſter graunted, at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the Generall <hi>Real.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 26. we tooke our leaue of the Generall, who moſt friendly welcomed and ſhewed vs great fauour, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying our Maſter and the Marchant with Auncients diſplayed, to our ſhips, whereof the one was the <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Starre,</hi> which the 22. of September came thither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the road by vs, intending to ſayle to <hi>Motir,</hi> but we to <hi>Bantam.</hi> We tooke the Marchant of the <hi>Starre,</hi> and one of the Generals men with vs to <hi>Bantam,</hi> at the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals intreatie.</p>
            <p>The 27. wee paſt by <hi>Tidore,</hi> there the <hi>Morning Starre</hi> left vs, and made towards <hi>Motir.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 28. wee paſt <hi>Motir</hi> and <hi>Makian.</hi> The 29. <hi>Caiou,</hi> and <hi>Bakian,</hi> and that day paſt the fourth time vnder the <hi>Equinoctiall</hi> Line.</p>
            <p>The 2. of October we ſayled by <hi>Loga, Combella,</hi> and <hi>Manipa</hi> in <hi>Zeira,</hi> and the 3. by <hi>Burro.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 6. we paſt by <hi>Button,</hi> and <hi>Cabeſſecabinco,</hi> and the ſeuenth by <hi>Cabona.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 8. we paſt the point of <hi>Bugarones,</hi> betweene the ſouth poynt of <hi>Celebes</hi> and <hi>Deſolaſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 13. about euening, we had a ſight of the Iſland of <hi>Madura.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 14. In the morning, we ſaw <hi>Iaua,</hi> and that day ſayled by <hi>Tuban.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 16. about noone, we came before <hi>Iapara,</hi> where we anchored in the Road, and there found the ſhip cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:17309:45"/>the <hi>Holland</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> which lay there to lade Ryce, to carry it to <hi>Tarnata.</hi> At <hi>Iapara</hi> there is all kinde of victuals to be had in great aboundance, and good cheape. There wee bought much Ryce, Arack, Fleſh, Fiſh, and other victuals, wherewith we meant to ſayle home.</p>
            <p>The 23. we ſet ſayle, and the 28. went by <hi>Iacatra,</hi> where wee anchored without the Iſland, there wee found three ſhipps of <hi>Holland.</hi> The <hi>Horne,</hi> the <hi>Eagle,</hi> and the <hi>Trou,</hi> and 3. Engliſh ſhippes. The next night, one of our men died, which was the firſt man that died that voyage in the <hi>Vnitie,</hi> beſides 2. more that die in the <hi>Horne,</hi> the one <hi>Iohn Corneliſon Schouten,</hi> our maſters brother, In the ſouth ſea, by the <hi>Dogs Iſland,</hi> and one about the coaſt of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingale,</hi> ſo that vntill then, there died but 3. men in both the ſhips, and then we had left 84. men liuing, all indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently well.</p>
            <p>The 31. the ſhippe called <hi>Bantam,</hi> with <hi>Iohn Peterſon Koeuen</hi> of <hi>Horne</hi> Preſident of <hi>Bantam,</hi> for the Eaſt <hi>India</hi> company, came before <hi>Iacatra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 1. of Nouember, the Preſident <hi>Iohn Peterſon Koe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> ſent for <hi>William Corneliſon Schouten</hi> our maſter, and the Marchants to come on land, where being come, (in the preſence of his counſell there aſſembled) he told them in name of the eaſt <hi>Indian</hi> Company, that they muſt leaue their ſhippe and goods their and deliuer it vp into his hands: and although our maſter ſhewed him many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to perſwade the contrarie, ſaying that they did them great wrong, they were forced to doe as the Preſident ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them, who told them, that if they thought they did them wrong, that they ſhould right themſelues in <hi>Holland:</hi> and ſo our ſhip and goods was ſtayed, and atta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched there. To receiue the ſhip and all her furniture, the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:17309:46"/>Preſident appointed two maſters of ſhipps, and two Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, which was deliuered by inuentory vnto them, by our maſter and the Marchant. This was done vpon Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the firſt of Nouember, after our reckoning but vpon a Tewſday the ſecond of Nouember, by our countrimens reckoning there. The reaſon of the difference of the time fell out thus, as we ſayled weſtward from our owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and had with the ſunne compaſſed the Globe of the world, we hadde one night, or ſun-ſetting leſſe then they: and they that come out of the weſt and ſayle to the eaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thereby had one day or ſun-ſetting more then we, which make a quarter difference, and ſo as we made our recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the time then with our ſelues, and did the like with our countrimen, that weeke we loſt the Tweſdaie, leaping from Munday to wedneſdaie, and ſo hadde one weeke of 6. dayes.</p>
            <p>Our ſhip being in this manner taken from vs, ſome of our men put themſelues into ſeruice with the eaſt <hi>Indian</hi> company. The reſt were put into two ſhips, (that were to goe home into <hi>Holland</hi>) called the <hi>Amſterdam</hi> and the <hi>Zeland:</hi> their generall, being <hi>George van Spielbergher,</hi> The maſter <hi>William Corneliſon Schouten,</hi> and <hi>Iacob le Maire,</hi> 10. of our men, went with the generall in the <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> The maſters name <hi>Iohn Corneliſon May, alias Meuſcheater,</hi> and <hi>Aris Clawſon</hi> and the Pilot <hi>Claus Peterſon</hi> with 10. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the <hi>Zeland,</hi> the maſters name <hi>Cornelis Riemlande</hi> of <hi>Midleburgh,</hi> which ſet ſayle from <hi>Bantam</hi> the 14. of December.</p>
            <p>The 32. our Marchant <hi>Iacob le Maire</hi> died.</p>
            <p>The 1. of Ianuary 1617. Wee loſt the ſight of the <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 24. Wee were vnder the Iſland <hi>Mauriciuus</hi> at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, where wee refreſht our ſelues, and the 30. ſet ſayle
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:17309:46"/>from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce.</p>
            <p>The 6. of March, as we geſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, we paſt the cape, but ſaw it not.</p>
            <p>The 31. Wee were vnder the Iſland of <hi>Saint Helena.</hi> Where we found the <hi>Zeland,</hi> which arriued there certaine dayes before vs.</p>
            <p>The 6. of Aprill after wee had refreſht our ſelues, and taken in freſhe water, both our ſhips ſet ſayle, and the 14. of Aprill ſaw the Iſland <hi>Aſcention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 23. we ſaw 2 ſhips to loofeward from vs vnder one degree, ſouthward of the line, but becauſe wee could not reach them, we held on our courſe. The 24. in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wee were the fift time vnder the Equinoctiall line, and the 28. we ſaw the north ſtarre, which wee had not ſeene in 20. monthes before. The 1. of Iuly we came with the <hi>Amſterdam</hi> into <hi>Zeland,</hi> where the day before, the <hi>Zeland</hi> likewiſe was arriued: And ſo performed our voyage in two yeares, and eighteene dayes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
